[Music]
[Musique]
Pierre Connaissa, hello, hello. We're
pierre connaissa bonjour bonjour Nous
interviewing you today for a
vous interrogons aujourd'hui pour une
YouTube channel called Serview. We'd like to
chaîne Youtube qui s'appelle Serview on
get your
aurait aimé avoir un peu votre point de
perspective on recent events. What
vue sur les récents événements qu'est-ce
can you
que vous pouvez nous en
tell us about them? A little bit of background, and
dire petit petit point biographique et
then a little bit of history.
puis petit point de retour en arrière
Well, I worked for about twenty
bon moi j'ai travaillé une vingtaine
years at the French Ministry of
d'années dans les au ministère de la
Defense in various roles,
Défense français sur différ
all but
domaines poste tout tout sauf de
administration. Specifically,
l'administration c'est-à-dire affairire
strategic affairs, arms exports,
stratégique exportation d'armement
intelligence, and more generally,
renseignement puis d'une manière
thinking about the organization of the
générale réflexion sur l'organisation du
ministry. I left that position in the early
ministère poste que j'ai quitté au début
2000s to run a
des années 2000 pour diriger une société
business intelligence company for about
intelligence économique pendant environ
eight years. And now I'm doing well, I'm
8 ans et maintenant ça va je suis
happily retired because I can do what I
retraité heureux parce que je peux faire
want to do, which is
ce que j'ai envie de faire c'est-à-dire
actually writing. I'm free to
en fait écrire je suis libéré de la
speak, if you will. Okay, so the first,
parole si vous voulez bon alors premier
extremely important point, which
premier aspect extrêmement important qui
will perhaps explain
va peut-être expliquer plus précisément
my way of
mon mode de
thinking more precisely, is that I was working on
réflexion j'étais donc sur les affaires
strategic affairs in the 90s. The
stratégiques dans les la décennie 90 la
90s was the time when the USSR...  It's a
décennie 90 c'est le moment où l'URSS
bad joke to
nous fait la mauvaise blague de
disappear, that's what
disparaître he c'est ce que dit le
Gorbachev's advisor said at the Helsinki summit to
conseiller de gorbachov au sommet
the American team: "We're going to do you
à au type de à l'équipe de américaine on
the
va vous faire la on va vous rendre le
worst possible service, we're going to deprive you of..."
pire des services on va vous priver d'
So it seems like a joke, but in fact,
alors ça paraît une blague mais en fait
in the strategic thinking system,
dans le système de réflexion stratégique
it's obviously traumatic because
c'est évidemment un traumatisme parce
how can you think about
que comment voulez-vous réfléchir au
risk, threats, or challenges when you
risque aux menaces au au défi quand vous
no longer have enemies? That is to say, either
n'avez plus d'ennemis c'est-à-dire soit
you have temporary layoffs, so you
vous avez le chômage technique donc vous
lay people off and then you think
licenciez et puis vous pensez que les
budgets will decrease, or you create
budgets vont disminuer soit vous créez
enemies. What do you mean
de l'ennemi qu'est-ce que vous entendez
by creating enemies? Well, creating
par créer de l'ennemi ben créer de
enemies is what everyone saw
l'ennemi c'est ce que tout le monde a vu
appear in the 90s, that is to say,
paraître dans les années 90 c'est-à-dire
an American line of thinking consisting,
une réflexion américaine consistant à
in particular, of... a burst
dire consistant en particulier à à fusé
of thought, such as the
de la pensée comme par exemple le le
clash of civilizations, such as
choc des civilisations comme par exemple
Tington's book, or such as
le le bouquin du tington ou comme par
the end of history,
exemple la fin de la fin de l'histoire
Fukuyama's book. Each time, it's these
le bouquin de Fukuyama chaque fois c ces
themes.  which I will come back to,
thématiques sur lesquel je reviendrai
was amplified, picked up, and disseminated by
était amplifiée reprise et diffusé par
all the media in all countries. To give
tous les médias de tous les pays pour
you an example, the book by the author was
vous prendre un exemple le bouquin du
translated into 35 languages. Now,
tinton a été traduit en 35 langues bon
it raised an issue on
or il posait une problématique sur
which one could have an
laquelle on pouvait avoir une distance
extremely important critical distance, since
critique extrêmement importante puisque
it assumed that there is a kind of
ça supposait que il y a une espèce de
Arab-Islamic world that was, by
monde araboislamique qui était et par
nature, aggressive, and that was obviously the
nature agressif et c'était évidemment le
American point of view on the matter. But from the
point de vue américain là-dessus mais à
moment the book was
partir du moment où le bouquin était
disseminated as the new
diffusé comme la nouvelle pensée
American thought, it formatted the entire debate. That is to
américaine ça formatait tout le débat
say, one could only
c'est-à-dire qu'on ne pouvait que se
position oneself for or against the book by this author.
positionner pour ou contre le bouquin
Okay, I'll take another
d'une tictone bon je prends un autre
example: either you are with us or you are
exemp soit vous êtes avec nous soit vous
against us. Yes, that's it. So what's
êtes contre nous oui c'est ça alors ce
funny is that when Bou
qui est rigolo c'est que Bou quand il
uses the phrase, he transforms the
utilise la phrase il transforme la
phrase from the Bible. That is to say, the
phrase de la Bible c'est-à-dire que la
phrase from the Bible is "all those who
phrase de la Bible c'est tous ceux qui
are not against us are with us,"
ne sont pas contre nous sont avec nous
and the phrase he uses is "all those who are
et la phrase de bouche c'était tous ceux
not with us are against us." It's a
qui sont pas avec nous sont contre nous
funny change.  It's
c'est rigolo comme changement c'est
ancient, meaning he was taking the
antique c'est-à-dire que il reprenait la
biblical phrase in its most exclusive form, the one most
phrase de la Bible dans la forme la plus
likely to create
nature à créer du
conflict. So, this other
conflit bon et donc le cette autre
example, which you might find fascinating, is
exemple qui voulez qu' est fascinant
Fukuyama's book. He was
c'est l'exemple du bouquin de Fukuyama
one of the mouthpieces in
qui va être un des soutiens de bouche en
Iraq, supporting
Irak qui va favoriser qui va soutenir
the American aggression there. His thesis
l'agression américaine en Irak sa thèse
was simply the end of history, the
était simplement la fin de l'histoire le
liberal democratic model would
modèle démocratique libéral va être
triumph. So, ultimately, in a way, there's no
triomphé donc finalement d'une certaine
more history. You
manière il y a plus d'histoire bon vous
've seen the success of the thesis; we ca
avez vu le succès de la thèse on peut
n't really say it was a forward-looking
pas dire que ce soit effectivement une
vision that translated
vision prospective qui s'est traduite
into reality. But what
dans la réalité bon mais ce qui m'a
interested me much more was the way
intéressé beaucoup plus c'était la façon
every time an American book appeared, there was a
dont à chaque fois paraissait un bouquin
kind of
américain vous avez une espèce de
mobilization of all the newspapers,
mobilisation de tous les les journaux
dailies, news outlets, doing
les quotidiens les news à chaque fois
interviews, debates, and so on. Is this
faisant des interviews des débats et
mobilization or
cetera sur C mobilisation ou une
propaganda? Well, I leave it to the media, how can I put it?
propagande ben moi je donne je laisse
I consider that the
comment dire le je considère que les
media are free to make their
médias sont libres de leurs choix
editorial choices, and therefore I don't take them on board.
éditoriaux et donc que je les prends pas
For legal professionals, it's
pour des auxiliaires de justice c'est
not their area of ​​expertise; they're essentially trying to
pas leur sujet ils essayent de fait de
capitalize on current events. How news is
surfer sur ce qui est l'actualité
created
comment comment se crée l'actualité
is another question, but generally speaking, as soon as
après ça c'est une autre question mais
you have a topic that generates
moment où vous avez un sujet qui fait le
buzz, you
buzz ben vous avez
immediately get media coverage.
immédiatement une reprise par les médias
So, what interested me much more was
bon donc ce qui m'a beaucoup plus
ultimately how this
intéressé c'est finalement comment
strategic production mechanism works. We're all used to
stratégique alors on est tous habitués
talking about the military-industrial complex, for example. The
par exemple à parler du complexe
military-
militaro industriel complexe militaro
industrial complex means the conjunction
industriel ça veut dire la conjonction
of the military with
des militaires avec les industriels de
defense industry, which is supposedly the
la défense qui seraient les faiseurs de
war-makers. But I was at the Ministry of
guerre or moi j'étais au ministère de la
Defense, and what I observed was that
Défense et ce que je constatais c'est
the military wasn't at all
que les militaires étaient pas du tout
belligerent, firstly because they know what
bellicistes d'abord parce qu'ils savent
war is, if you
ce que c'est que la guerre si vous
will. And on the other hand, there was a
voulez et que par contre fonctionnait un
kind of military-intellectual complex at work,
espèce de complexe militaro intellectuel
composed in particular of "singank" (a term used to describe intellectuals who
composé en particulier des singank qui
produce these famous books) by a
produisait ces fameux bouquins d'un
number of media intellectuals and
certain nombre d'intellectuels
academics. And then, of course, within
de de service académique et puis
the ministries, there's a
évidemment à l'intérieur des ministères
strategic thinking system.
de système de réflexion stratégique
I'm opening up...  As an aside, within
j'ouvre une parenthèse est-ce qu'au sein
these institutions, did you see a
de ces institutions vous avez vu une une
conjunction of people trained
une conjonction de personnes ayant été
in the United States or adhering to
formées aux États-Unis ou ayant une
American doctrine?
doctrine américaine pas à ce moment-là
Not at that time. It was more a generational
pas à ce moment-là on était plutôt si
shift, if you will.
vous voulez dans une relève
For example,
générationnelle c'est-à-dire par exemple
Sovietologists were already losing
les soviétologue étaient déjà en perte
ground since the
de vitesse puisqu'il y avait plus de
Soviet Union no longer existed, and they were desperately fighting
Union soviétique et cela se battait
to maintain control over the former
désespérément pour garder si vous voulez
Soviet republics that had become
exemple les anciens pays de l'URSS
independent. A major
devenu indépendants gros débat
administrative debate ensued: should the
administratif c'est estce que les pays
newly independent Central Asian countries fall under the
d'Asie centrale nouvellement indépendant
Turkic or Persian world, depending on the
doivent relever du monde turc ou persan
language spoken, or should they
langue qui parlait ou au contraire
fall under the USSR because they
relever de l'exurss parce qu' ils
were former Soviet republics?
étaient anciens pays S soviétique voyez
So, it was amusing because it was a
par exemple donc c'était rigolo parce
kind of dispute over
que c'était une espèce de querelle
expertise, but it was actually a
d'expertise mais qui était en fait un
power struggle: how could I
enjeu de pouvoir comment est-ce que je
remain an advisor to the prince? No, the
reste conseiller du prince non la relève
generational shift came later. In
générationnelle est arrivée plus tard en
particular, it's the generation in
particulier c'est celle qui est au
power today, that is, people
pouvoir aujourd'hui c'est-à-dire de gens
who have had this kind of...  The
qui ont eu cette espèce de
fascination with American power stems from the fact
fascination de la puissance américaine
that the 1990s were the
parce que la décennie 90 c'est la
decade of hyperpower and
décennie de l'hyperpuissance de de
unilateralism. There was no longer a
l'unilatéralisme il y a plus de rival
truly strategic and coherent rival to
cohérent réellement stratégique à à
the Union, only to the United States. Therefore, at that time, there was
l'Union aux États-Unis et donc à ce
a kind of fascination with
moment-là une espèce de fascination sur
how the majority leader would act, how they would be
comment va faire le leader majoritaire
followed, what
comment est-ce qu'on va le suivre quelle
position to adopt towards them, and
position on adopte vis-àvis de lui et
so on. The last vestige
cetera et la dernière survivance
of
goalienne si vous voulez de la
French diplomacy, if you will, is
diplomatie française c'est la réaction
Shirak's reaction of refusing to go to Iraq. After that, everything else
de Shirak refusant d'aller en Irak après
was swept aside:
ça si vous voulez tout le reste est
Sarkozy, Hollande, and so forth. All of this
balayé Sarkozi Hollande et cetera tout
became a kind of generation of
ça devient une espèce de génération de
neoconservatives, partly educated in the
néoconservateurs en partie formé aux
United States, or at least
États-Unis ou en tout cas ayant une
fascinated by it, who
fascination pour les États-Unis et qui
would follow the Americans even more than the
vont suivre plus même encore que les
British, if you will, pretty much
Britanniques si voulez les Américains à
everywhere in the world. Perhaps
peu près partout dans le monde peut-être
a word about the American Young
un petit mot sur les amerriican young
Leaders on this subject. Listen, what
leaders justement à ce propos écoutez
's very surprising is that this
c'est ce qui est très étonnant c'est que
attitude is completely internalized.  That is to say, there is no longer
attitude c'est-à-dire qu'il y a plus
any critical distance. They won't
aucune distanciation critique ils vont
say, "I was trained by the CSIS," or "
pas dire j'ai été formé par le CSIS où
I was trained by..." Not at all. It's a
j'ai été formé par non pas du tout c'est
kind of... how to put it... they're almost fellow
une espèce de comment dire c'est presque
travelers, if you will.
des compagnons de route si vous voulez
As we used to say back in the USSR era,
comme on le disait à l'époque du l'URSS
these are people who retain their intellectual freedom, who have
c'est des gens qui gardent leur liberté
their freedom
d'esprit qui ont leur liberté
of expression, but who are totally
d'expression mais qui sont totalement
American-minded
American minded
today. And we see this, for
aujourd'hui et on le on le constate par
example, in the policy towards
exemple sur la politique à l'égard de
Iran, which is becoming completely
l'Iran qui devient totalement
incomprehensible. That is to say, since they didn't
incompréhensible c'est-à-dire comme ils
see the American shift, they're going to be
n'ont pas vu le virage américain ils
forced to backtrack, if
vont être obligés de rétropédaler si
you will, to say, "But after all,
vous voulez pour se dire mais après tout
now we need Iran to
maintenant on a besoin de l'Iran pour
resolve the Iraqi crisis, to
résoudre la crise irakienne pour
resolve Afghanistan, to resolve the
résoudre l'Afghanistan pour résoudre la
crises in Lebanon and Syria." So we're
crise au Liban et en Syrie et C donc on
in a situation where, if you
est dans une situation où si vous
will, the
voulez la génération qui est
current generation of strategists is
actuellement celle des stratégistes est
a generation that is precisely completely out of touch with
une génération qui est justement
reality. So how does this
réalité alors comment se passe le
phenomenon play out? It's quite interesting because,
phénomène c'est assez intéressant parce
for example...  In the 1990s, we
que par exemple dans les années 90 on
were in the midst of the crisis in Yuoslavia.
était donc dans la crise en youoslavie
The crisis in Yuoslavia was
la crise en youoslavie était
indeed a crisis that
effectivement une crise qui nous
directly concerned us because of the
concernait directement à cause de la
continental situation, because it was, after all,
disposition continental à cause du fait
one of the countries occupied by
européens un des pays occupés par
Germany, one of the countries that had suffered the most
l'Allemagne qui avait le plus souffert
from the German occupation, which had had
de l'occupation allemande qui avait eu
concentration camps and so on. And
les camps de concentration et cetera or
in Yuoslavia, we found a
ont retrouva en youoslavie un certain
number of similar behaviors:
nombre de comportements les camp
Serbian concentration camps to imprison
concentration serbees pour enfermer les
Croats, gang rapes—we
Croates les viols collectifs enfin on
had all of that. So, this
avait tout ça B donc la ça concernait
directly concerned Europeans, and
directement les Européens et les
at the time, Europeans thought that a
Européens à l'époque pensaient que une
Franco-British alliance would be enough to
alliance franco-anglaise suffirait à
calm everyone down. At that point, we
calmer tout le monde à ce moment-là on a
discovered that it wasn't even enough to
découvert que ça suffisait même pas à
dissuade the Serbs from doing what they
dissuader les Serbes de faire ce qu'ils
had to do. So, we realized
avaient à faireon donc là on s'est rendu
the weakness in relation to the
compte de la faiblesse à l'égard des
Americans, or rather, in relation to
Américains enfin plutôt à l'égard même
a middle power like Serbia,
d'une puissance moyenne comme la Serbie
and therefore the necessity of having
et donc de la nécessité d'avoir un appui
American support. This was a time when the
américain c'est c'était l'époque où les
Americans weren't particularly
Américains étaient pas spécialement
Bellic, meaning that the Clinton era
Bellic c'està-dire que l'époque Clinton
was a time when we had to pull them
était une époque où il a fallu les tirer
by the sleeve to get them to come. It was
par la manche pour qu'il vienne c'était
n't him; he considered it our
pas il il considérait que c'était notre
business. But we were also in a
affaire mais on était aussi dans un
period of economic crisis.
moment où crise économique est dedans si
Everyone was reducing their
vous voulez tout le monde réduisait son
defense budgets, everyone was somewhat
budget de défense tout le monde était un
reluctant, the Germans in
peu réticent les Allemands en
particular, to intervene militarily,
particulier à intervenir militairement
and so on. So there's also this shock,
et cetera ça donc il y a aussi ce choc
meaning that if we're
là c'est-à-dire le fait que si on n'est
not even capable of managing a
même pas capable de gérer une crise
European crisis on the scale of the
européenne du niveau de la crise
Yugoslav crisis, then we truly have
youoslave c'est que véritablement on a
two possible options: either we create a
deux options possibles soit on fait une
European defense force, but that becomes a
Europe de la défense mais ça devient un
philosophical debate, a bit like the
débat philosophique à peu près comme le
sex of angels, or we follow
sexe des anges ou alors on se met dans
the American path. And that's
le siillage américain et ça c'est
the option that was chosen
l'option qui s'est faite de manière
unconsciously and on which we have
inconsciente et sur laquelle on a
continually declined. So
ensuite continuellement décliné donc
the French intelligentsia, or
l'intelligigen française ou
the
l'intelligencia
Parisian intelligentsia, pushed to go in that
parisienne a poussé pour aller dans ce
direction. That is to say, it's the
sensl c'està-dire c'est c'est le
miserabilism of  Impotence is
misérabilisme de l'impuissance c'est le
intellectual miserabilism, it's the
misérabilisme intellectuel c'est c'est
unwillingness to
la le fait de ne pas vouloir se
distance oneself from the
soustraire du groupe
pro-US group. I don't think so. There were
pro US je crois que non il y a eu
several things. First, there was the
plusieurs choses d'abord il y a eu la
confrontation with reality, realizing that we, as Europeans,
confrontation à la réalité constater
were incapable of managing
qu'on était pas capable de gérer en tant
a crisis like
qu'Européen une crise comme la
Yugoslavia. That's a
youoslavie c'est quand même un constat
dramatic realization. It meant that on
dramatique ça voulait dire que sur le
European soil, we weren't even
territoire européen on éétait même pas
militarily capable of having a
capable militairement d'avoir une force
sufficiently
d'interposition qui soit suffisamment
deterrent interposition force. Don't forget that
dissuasive n'oubliez pas quand même que
the siege of Saravo lasted 1,000 days,
le siège de sarevo a duré 1000 jours
like the siege of Leningrad, mind you. Well, in
comme le siège de leningrade quand même
other times, obviously.
hein bon en d'utrre temps évidemment
This realization is already terrible: 2,500
déjà ce constat est terrible 2500
airstrikes. So then, there was indeed,
frappes aériennes bon alors ensuite il y
how to put it, this
avait effectivement comment dire cette
kind of force management that meant we didn't want to
espèce de gestion de la force qui
engage in
faisait qu'on voulait pas s'engager dans
a war. We wanted, at the same time, to
une guerre on voulait en même temps
have a sufficiently deterrent action so
avoir une action suffisamment dissuasive
that the Serbs wouldn't go too
pour que les Serbes soit n'aillent pas
far, but at the same time,
trop loin mais en même temps
remember, we let Gorasd do what he wanted. We let  To
rappelez-vous on a laissé faire gorasd
carry out occupations,
on a laissé faire des occupations avec
sometimes with massacres, all of which is
parfois des massacres le tout étant
obviously a crisis of
évidemment une crise de la conscience
European conscience, since once again it was
européenne puisque encore une fois
an admission of powerlessness. I'm coming back to the fact that
c'était un constat d'impuissance je
you're talking about the former
reviens puisque vous parlez de de de de
Yugoslavia, what do you think of the mass
l'exyugoslavie qu'est-ce que vous pensez
graves at Timy Soara? Well, that's more of
euh des charniers de Timy soara bah ça
a question for
c'est plutôt une question qui concerne
journalists. That is to say, when
les journalistes c'est-à-dire que quand
we're in a situation of
on est dans une situation de tension
media tension, like the days
médiatique comme par exemple les jours
we experienced last week, it's
qu'on a vécu la semaine dernière il est
obvious that there's an
évident qu'il y a une comment dire une
overproduction of information. I was a
surproduction d'information j'étais
guest on the EUR 1 set, I think it was
invité sur le plateau d'EUR 1 je crois
last Thursday or Friday.
que c'était jeudi ou vendredi dernier
Anyway, when the
enfin quand il y a eu la les forces de
police and gendarmerie forces decided
police et de gendarmerie ont décidé
to attack the two locations
d'attaquer les deux les deux endroits
held by
tenus par
the terrorists, it was
les par les terroristes
extraordinary because first
c'était extraordinaire parce que d'abord
the radio host was commenting on
le type de radio commentait des images
television images, then he asked his
de télévision ensuite il demandait à ces
specialist journalists to comment on the
spécialistes journalistes de commenter
television footage, and then, since it was
les trucs de télévision et puis comme il
necessary to maintain a kind of
fallait entretenir une espèce de tension
media tension, he would pass the microphone, one minute
médiatique il passait la parole un coup
to the correspondent who was in
au correspondant qui se trouvait à
Massin, the next  To the correspondent who was in
Massin un coup au correspondant qui se
Darie, and then the guys, they didn't have much to say.
trouvait à Darie et alors les types il
So the one
avaient pas grand chose à dire donc
in Darie was saying, "Well, yes, there are
celui de Darie disait ben oui il y a
two helicopters... no, maybe
deux hélicoptères qui sur non peut-être
three... no, there are maybe two." Well, that's an
trois non il y a peut-être deux bon ça
example of information that was supposed to be
c'est exemplement de l'information qui
information about the tension, but
était une information de la tension mais
which in fact didn't add anything. And Vincen
qui en fait n'apportait rien et Vincen
is even more of a caricature because the
c'est encore plus caricatural puisque le
guy in Vincen was saying, "Well, we're in contact
type de Vincen disait ben on a contact
with the neighbor who lives above
avec la voisine qui est au-dessus
the supermarket. The lady was saying, 'Well, listen,
l'upmarché la dame disait ben écoutez
I have nothing to tell you because first of all,
moi je rien à vous dire parce que
my windows face the other
d'abord mes fenêtres donent de l'autre
side, and then the police
côté puis ensuite les policiers m'ont
asked me not to close the windows.'
demandé de pas de fermer les fenêtres
Then he questioned the gas station attendant who
ensuite il interrogéit le pompiste qui
lived across from the hypermarket. The
habitait en face de l'hypermarché le
attendant was saying, 'But I can't tell you anything.'
pomist disait mais moi je peux rien vous
Shipwreck, the shipwreck of journalism, we're
dire nafrage le naufrage du journalisme
seeing it clearly with the emergence
on on le note bien avec l'émergence
of the Internet. The question I'm
d'Internet euh la question que je me
asking myself is, where are we going?
pose c'est où est-ce qu'on va
That is to say, we have an increase in
c'est-à-dire on a une augmentation des
threats, the weak signals are...
menaces les signaux faibles sont au
Red, we have, uh, some captains of
rouge on a euh des des des capitaines de
pedalos within the strategic
pédalo au sein des cellules stratégiques
and foresight cells, we
et de prospective on s'engage nous
Europeans get involved in Libyan conflicts, in
Européens dans des conflits libyens dans
Syrian conflicts, and
des conflits syriens et on se retrouve
then, with our mouths full of praise, we
ensuite avec la bouche en cœur on se
get repercussions and
prend des des des des répercussions et
terrorist attacks on
des des attaques terroristes sur sur le
French soil. So you're telling me
sol français donc vous êtes en train de
that we're not capable of
me dire que on n'est pas capable de
managing Kosovo, uh, that we get involved in
gérer le Kosovo euh qu'on s'engage sur
wars where the quagmire was
des guerres où l'enlisement était
predictable, and and we don't have any more money?
prévisible et et et on a plus d'argent
Yes, what interested me a lot,
oui le ce qui m'a beaucoup intéressé
particularly in the creation of
notamment dans la fabrication de
the enemy, is that I asked myself,
l'ennemi c'est que je me suis dit
ultimately, what period do we enter
finalement quelle période ouvre-t-on
after 1991? Because ultimately, having no more
après 91 parce que finalement nayant
enemies, why are there still
plus d'enemi pourquoi il y a-t-il encore
conflicts?
des conflits
And I find that, first of all,
et je trouve que d'abord la déclaration
Bush's declaration that followed 9/11 is
de Bush qui a suivi le 11 septembre est
extremely interesting because, for
extrêmement intéressante parce que pour
the first time, he declares war
la première fois il il déclare la guerre
on concepts, the war against
à des concepts la guerre contre la
proliferation and against terrorism,
prolifération et contre le terrorisme
which are, once again, not enemies, but
qui sont encore une fois pas des ennemis
concepts. And TER, concept
qui sont des concepts et TER concept
in the spin doctor sense, I think that  Yes, if
dans sens spin doctor je crois que si si
you like, he shapes
vous voulez il formate la domination
American domination of the world. That is to say, I
américaine sur le monde c'est-à-dire je
give you the agenda, I tell you that we
vous donne l'agenda je vous dis qu'il
must fight against
faut se battre contre le terrorisme
international terrorism—he's the one who invented this
international c'est lui qui inventre ce
concept—and then he performs this
concept et puis il fait ce r tour de
formidable strategic sleight of hand in which
passe-p stratégique formidable dans
he calls proliferation the
lequel il dit la prolifération la menace
main threat, even though 11 out of
principale alors qu'il y a 11 saoudiens
15 members of the
sur 15 membres de la de l'atque du 11
9/11 attack were Saudis in Iraq. And he says that the "
septembre sur le l'IRAC et il dit que
Attacks of Evil" are Iraq, Iran,
les l'AC du mal c'est l'IRAC l'Iran et
North Korea, and Saudi Arabia.
la Corée du Nord l'Arabie Saoudite
Nobody talks about it anymore. So that's what's
personne n'en parle plus donc c'est ça
interesting: how do we
qui est intéressant c'est-à-dire comment
conceive of an enemy that
est-ce qu'on va concevoir un ennemi dans
will shape the Western camp, in this
lequel on va formater le camp occidental
case, and immediately the
en l'espèce et immédiatement la
outcome—you know it—the invasion
déclinaison vous la connaissez invasion
of Afghanistan. We can
de l'Afghanistan on peut aujourd'hui
take stock today, and then immediately afterward,
dresser le bilan et puis immédiatement
Iraq—the first fracture.
dans la foulée l'Irak première fracture
So Afghanistan is interesting
alors l'Afghanistan est intéressant
because, with even a minimal amount
parce
of
que pour peu qu'on ait un minimum de
historical knowledge, everyone broke away.
connaissance historique tout le monde
The teeth on Afghanistan,
s'est cassé les dents sur l'Afghanistan
it's fantastic, the English in the good old days
c'est formidable les Anglais à la belle
of
époque du
colonialism, they really did, but then the
colonialisme ils ont hein mais alors les
English, they arrive all the way to Kabu and
Anglais ils arrivent jusqu'à Kabou et
then finally, seeing that they can't
puis finalement voyant qu'ils peuvent
hold the country, they burn down the
pas tenir le pays ils incendient le
Kabu bazaar. There's no bazaar in Kabu today, it's still
Kabou aujourd'hui c'est quand même
fantastic, you have to know that. And then, during the
fantastique faut le savoir et puis dans
retreat, they are caught in an
la dans le repli ils sont pris par une
attack at Khmer Pass where
attaque à la kber pass où est exterminé
the entire British expeditionary force is exterminated
la totalité du corps expéditionnaire
except for
britannique sauf
one. The Afghans send a guy to
un les afgans s'ent un type pour qu'il
tell the others what happened.
aille raconter aux autres qui s'est
No, no, but precisely, it's the
passé non non mais justement c'est la
first time that this thing was created,
première fois que la chose était crée
it wasn't created by the
elle était pas créée par la la puissance
dominant strategic power, it was created
stratégique dominante elle étit créée
by a bunch of vanupids who were the
par une bande de vanupied qui était les
Afghans of the time. The Soviets, 10
Afghans de l'époque les Soviétiques 10
years there, the result, you
ans sur place le résultat vous le
know it: 4 million refugees in
connaissez 4 millions de réfugiés au
Pakistan, 2 million refugees in Iran,
Pakistan 2 millions de réfugiés en Iran
and finally they leave Afghanistan, and
et finalement il quitte l'Afghanistan et
completely disregarding that, I
ne tenant absolument pas compte de ça je
'm pretty certain that the world that surrounded them
suis à peu près certain que le monde qui
at the time of the  The
entourait bouche au moment de la
decision was made by people who, having never even
décision étaiit des gens qui n'ayant
set foot in
jamais mis le pied de toute façon en
Afghanistan, were saying, "But Afghanistan, we'll
Afghanistan disaient mais Afghanistan on
take care of it right away. We'll
va faire notre affaire tout de suite on
catch Ben Ladan, we'll overthrow
va attraperer ben ladan on va renverser
Mullah Omar, and you'll see, the
le Mola Omar et vous allez voir les
Taliban will be swept away." It's true
talibans vont être balayés c'est vrai
that the Taliban were swept away.
que les talibans ont étent balayés
The problem is that they weren't
le problème c'est queils étaient pas au
aware that the war was over. You
courant que la guerre était finie vous
know, it's like
savez c'est comme la déclaration de
George Buou's declaration during the invasion of
George buou quand il y a l'invasion en
Iraq. The first phase, the
Irak la première phase phase
conventional phase, the regime,
conventionnelle le régime l'armée de
Saddam Hussein's army, was swept away, and then George
Saddam Hussein est balayé et puis George
Buou gave this fantastic speech on
bouche fait ce fantastique discours sur
the aircraft carrier saying, "That's it, we've
le porteavion disant c'est bon on a
won." Well, the problem is that the
gagné bon le problème c'est que les
others weren't informed that the
autres sont étaient pas informés que la
war wasn't over, and they
guerre était pas finie et ils ont
continued. And so, today, to
continué et donc on est aujourd'hui pour
return to the case of Afghanistan, after
reprendre le cas de l'Afghanistan après
a particularly
un bilan qui est particulièrement
catastrophic outcome, since they've been there for 13 years,
catastrophique puisque ça fait 13 ans
the same defense effort as
sur place le même effort de défense que
the Soviets: 6 trillion dollars. 6 trillion
les Soviétiques 6000 milliards 6000
dollars if we count everything.  This is a
milliards si on compte la totalité c'est
point we can come back to if
un point sur lequel on pourra revenir si
you like; that is to say, the entirety,
vous voulez c'estàdire la totalité c'est
including the cost of the wounded, the cost of
compris le coûp des blessés le coût des
compensation, the cost of the widows, and so on.
indemnités le cûp des veuves et cetera
And in the 6 trillion, I'm not counting
et dans les 6000 milliards je compte pas
veterans
les vétérant
and another important strategic aspect:
et autre aspect stratégique important
the extension of the war into Pakistan
l'extension de la guerre au Pakistan
because the Soviets were
parce que les Soviétiques c'était
always forbidden from crossing the
toujours interdit de franchir la
border, while
frontière tandis que les frappes de
drone strikes hit the territory, the
dronees frappent sur le territoire la
tribal areas, and thus the extension of the
zone tribale et donc l'extension de la
war. The outcome of all this, you
guerre bilan de tout ça vous le
know, is a
connaissez c'est-à-dire un retour
probable return of the Taliban. So the
probable des taliban alors le régime
Najibula regime, which succeeded the
najiboula qui avait succédé au
Soviets—excuse me, you're not talking about it, not at all, not at all, not at all—
soviétique par pardon vous parlez pas
and so the, how to put it, the Najibula
et donc le le comment dire le najiboula
that the Russians left in place after
que les Russes laissent en place après
their departure lasted two years. We can bet on
leur départ tient 2 ans on peut prendre
how long the Afghan regime will last
le Paris de savoir combien va tenir le
today; the outcome is
aujourd'hui bilan
catastrophic. For pity's sake, madam, and out of magnanimity,
catastrophique par pitié dame et par
I won't dwell on
grandeur d'ame je n'insisterai pas sur
the French operation in Libya, but we
l'opération française en Libye mais on
are exactly in that situation.
est exactement dans cette situation là
We'll come back to that, since you brought it up,
on va revenir sur puisque vous l'évoquez
BL
BL
Bernard-Henri Lévy,
Bernard Henry levvi
practically appointed Minister of
bombardé pratiquement ministre des
Foreign Affairs,
Affaires étrangères
alongside John McCain, in
euh au côté de J McCain sur cette sur
some photos—or at least not in
certaines photos du moins pas sur
some photos, but in the company of
certaines photos mais en compagnie de
John McCain on the territory. What do
John mccin sur le territoire qu'est-ce
you think of that? So, if
que vous en pensez ça que c'est alors si
you want, I talked to you about the
vous voulez le je vous ai parlé de la
generation, or rather, the concept of
génération enfin de la du concept de
war, which was the war against the
guerre qui était la guerre contre les
concepts. That was...  With
concepts ça c'était le production
American production today, we are forced to
américaine aujourd'hui on est obligé de
acknowledge that there is no
faire le constat qu'il y a pas de menace
strategic threat. Terrorism has never
stratégique le terrorisme n'a jamais
won a war, so even if
permis de gagner une guerre donc même le
terrorism is serious, if it kills
terrorisme si c'est grave si ça tue des
people, etc., it remains that it is not
gens et cetera ça reste que ce n'est pas
a strategic threat on the scale of what
une menace stratégique de l'ampleur de
the Red Army was in the
ce qui était l'Armée rouge dans les
1950s to 2000. So, we are now in
années de 50 à 2000 bon donc on est
an era where, if we
aujourd'hui dans une époque où si on
look at all the conflicts tearing
regarde l'ensemble des conflits qui
the planet apart, there are roughly
déchir la planète il y en a à peu près
400. But how do we make this choice to
400 mais comment fait-on ce choix pour
say which one is serious and which one isn't?
dire celui-là est grave celui-là n'est
Economic interest isn't the only factor.
pas grave intérêt économique pas
Because
seulement pas seulement parce que
you have this category of
justement vous avez cette catégorie de
people, the
gens qui sont sont les intellectuels
media intellectuals. There are new
médiatiques il y a des nouveaux si vous
opinion-makers on
voulez faiseurs d'opinion en matière
strategic matters, the first of which are the
stratégique les premiers c'est les
media intellectuals, in the
intellectuels médiatiques dans la
category that includes Bernard-Henri Lévy (BHL),
catégorie dans laquelle entre BHL
first point. But there are also
premier point mais il y a aussi les
humanitarians who tell you, "I know the
humanitaires qui vous disent je connais
victims, therefore I know the perpetrators."
les victimes donc je connais les
And then you have the
bourreaux et puis vous avez les
diasporas who will tell you, "In the name of..."  The
diasporas qui vont vous dire au nom de
suffering I endured 50
la la souffrance que j'ai subi il y a 50
years ago—I'll explain why
ans je vais vous expliquer pourquoi
our country must commit to this or
notre pays doit s'engager vers telle ou
that category. For example, if you want to talk about the
telle catégorie exemple si vous voulez
diaspora, it was the Armenian diaspora
de diaspora c'est la diaspora arménienne
that succeeded in getting that
qui a réussi à faire voter cette loi
stupid law passed, making France recognize
stupide qui fait que la France reconnaît
the genocide in which it played
le génocide dans lequel elle n'a
absolutely no part, so it can
strictement pas
go around lecturing
participé pour aller dé donner des
others. But are we going to
leçons aux autres mais est-ce qu'on va
pass a law on the genocide of the
voter une loi sur le génocide des
Indians, for example? Out of the
Indiens par exemple il en est pas
question. Are Algerians going to
question est-ce que les Algéries va
pass a law on the genocide of the
voter une loi sur le génocide des
FLN fighters for France? No, out of the
combattants du FLN pour la France non il
question. So you see this
en est pas question donc voyez cette
habit of people who will tell you, "
habitude de gens qui vont vous dire euh
France absolutely must recognize," that there is
la France doit absolument reconnaître
a force of
que fait que il y a une force de
pressure. Victimology is an
pression la victimologie est un levier
important lever, if you will, for determining
important si vous voulez pour déterminer
the axes of foreign policy. So,
les axes de la politique étrangère donc
these three
si vous c'est ces trois faiseurs
opinion leaders are the ones who interested me because they
d'opinion qui m'ont intéressé parce que
speak directly to
ceuxl ils s'adressent directement au
politicians; they don't go through analyses
politiqu il passe pas par des analyses
saying, "Invention, the most
disant invention le concept le plus
extraordinary concept that has been invented recently."
extraordinaire qu'on a inventé récemment
Well, you remember...
bon vous souvenez l'ingérence
Humanitarian intervention in Somalia, yes,
humanitaire en Somalie oui l'ingérence
humanitarian intervention, it was the warlords,
humanitaire c'était les chefs de guerre
international aid to Somalia, to the
P l'aide internationale à la Somalie au
poor people of Somalia, and so it is
pauvres gens de Somalie et donc il faut
absolutely necessary to make a defense effort
absolument faire un effort de défense
to
pour
re-establish a central power that would
rétablir un pouvoir central qui allait
finally manage aid to the population. Well, plus
enfin gérer l'aide de population bon
several errors, first the "
plus plusieurs erreurs d'abord la
me" strategy, because
stratégie de l' moi parce que
ultimately we saw that if I take a step back,
finalement on a vu que si je prends à
if today everyone doesn't care what is
distance si aujourd'hui tout le monde se
happening in Somalia, so there was indeed
fout ce qui se passe en Somalie donc il
a media moment that
y avait bien un moment médiatique qui
had sparked "me" and called on
avait suscité de l' moi et qui appelait
politicians to do something. It's
le politique à faire quelque chose c'est
generally the thin little child
en général c'est le petit enfant maigre
holding out their hand for a little
qui tend la main pour avoir un peu de
rice, it can be that. So you have
riz ça peut être ça alors vous avez
different "me" strategies, you
différentes stratégies de l' mois vous
have women, rape, little children, little girls,
avez les fmes viol petit enfant la
child soldiers, and so that's
petites fille les enfants soldats et ce
the media channel through which it
donc ça c'est le canal médiatique par
passes, but at the same time you
lequel ça passe mais en même temps vous
have the
avez là-dessus les intellectuels
media intellectuals who will tell you we cannot not,
médiatiques qui vont vous dire nous ne
the double negative
pouvons pas ne pas la double négation
that will explain that we absolutely must
qui va expliquer qu'il faut absolument y
go, and so we invent with Coucher
aller et donc on invente avec couchner
and Betati the idea...  Humanitarian management—
et betati l'idée la gérance humanitaire
so why humanitarian management?
alors pourquoi la gérance humanitaire
It's very interesting because
c'est très intéressant parce que les
humanitarians had the wind in their
humanitaires avaient le vent le vent en
sails since the 1960s, since
pou depuis les années 60 depuis le
Biafra. It was the type of
Biafra c'était le type d'action
non-state international action that
internationale non étatique dans laquel
everyone identified with, so there was
tout le monde se reconnaissait donc il y
political capital that absolutely had to be
a un capital politique qu'il fallait
recovered. And so
absolument récupérer et donc qu'on a
the concept of humanitarian intervention was invented, that is
inventé le concept d'ingérance
to say, associating the
humanitaire c'est-à-dire associé du
military with humanitarian aid. So the
militaire à l'humanitaire donc le le
concept of humanitarian bombing—that's
concept de bombardement humanitaire
not just bombing, it means equipping, how to
c'est ça pas seulement de bombardement
say, associating
comment dire associer les convois
humanitarian convoys with armed forces. This is because
humanitaires à des forces armées donc
humanitarian workers have
c'est par que les min humanitaires ont
always denounced it, saying, "No, what we need for
toujours dénoncé en disant mais non nous
our security is not to
ce qui demande notre sécurité c'est de
be armed, to appear
ne pas être armé c'est d'apparaître
non-belligerent." And so this
comme non belligérant et donc cette
militarization, which was mainly initiated
mixion qui a été principalement initiée
by Coucher, was, "We are going to
par couchner c'était nous allons
militarize humanitarian action." Well,
militariser l'action humanitaire bon le
you know the rest. Today,
reste vous le connaissez aujourd'hui
humanitarians have become
c'est que les humanitaires sont devenus
targets by force of circumstance,
des cibles par la force des choses
since no one can...
puisque plus personne ne peut les
Consider them independent, then, having
considérer comme indépendants alors pour
listened to some bearded
avoir écouté certains certaines
individuals who attack
personnes un peu barbues qui se s'en
humanitarian organizations, they tell me, "
prennent au C humanitaire ils me disent
We're attacking them because there are
voilà on s'en prend à eux parce que il y
strong suspicions of
a de grosses suspicions d'injection de
intelligence service infiltration within
de service de renseignement au sein de
these
ces uvres
humanitarian efforts. It's probable, it's possible, it might be
humanitaires c'est probable c'est c'est
true, it
possible c'est c'est peut-être vrai
might not be true, I don't know." But the mere
peut-être pas vrai je ne sais pas mais
fact that suspicion
du coup le seul fait que la suspicion
exists, just as it does regarding journalists,
existe de même que sur les journalistes
justifies the same type of
justifie le même type de comportement
hostile behavior. And so, where
d'hostilité et donc là où les
humanitarians were protecting themselves precisely
humanitaires se protégeaient justement
through their professed pacifism,
par leur pacifisme
the question arises as to how
pose la question de savoir quel va être
the belligerents will behave.
le comportement des belligérants bon
But the fundamental upheaval is
mais le bouleversement fondamental c'est
this concept of humanitarian intervention, which
ce concept d'ingérance humanitaire qui
will translate in Somalia into
va se traduire en Somalie par le fait
American troops landing in
américaines qui vont débarquer en
Somalia in the middle of the night, under the flashes and
Somalie en pleine nuit sous les flash et
glare of
sous les sunlight des journalistes de
television journalists. These guys are crawling on the
télévision c'est les mecs rempent par
ground with their faces blackened, and at the
terre avec le visage tout noir et en
same time, they're all around...
même temps ils sont autour il y a autour
From them, journalists filmed them
d'eux des journalistes qui les filment
live so that in the United States, people would
en direct pour qu'aux États-Unis on
know that they were arriving—a
sache que les j ils arrivve mise scène
fantastic production, sorry, a fantastic production, yes, a
formidable pardon une mise en scène
fantastic production, but
formidable oui mise en scène formidable
totally contradictory on the
pu totalement contradictoire sur le plan
military level. So we were in something
militaire donc on était dans quelque
that, obviously, at some point, would end up
chose qui évidemment à un moment ou un
clashing. The second
autre finirait par clasher deuxième
aspect that seems very interesting to me
aspect qui me paraît très intéressant
is the lack of political analysis on
c'est l'absence d'analyse politique sur
the crisis that we will find in Libya, that we
la crise qu'on va retrouver en Libye
will find in Syria, and so on.
qu'on va retrouver en Syrie et cetera
Why? Because political analysis
pourquoi parce que l'analyse politique
requires a minimum of looking
suppose qu'on fasse un minimum de retour
back before making a decision. But
en arrière avant de décider
the media perspective is not the
or le Pô médiatique n'est pas le Pô
strategic perspective, you know. If a politician
stratégique hein si vous un politique
is called upon, you can't help but be approached
est interpellé vous ne pouvez pas ne pas
by a media intellectual, by
par un intellectuel médiatique par des
humanitarians, and so on. He will decide in an
humitaire et cetera il va décider dans
emergency. So why insist on
l'urgence alors pourquoi jeiniste sur la
Somalia? Because Somalia is like
Somalie parce la Somalie c'est
Afghanistan; it's the country that
l'Afghanistan c'est le pays qui a
resisted colonization in exactly the
résisté aux colonisation exactement de
same way: tribal structures,
la même manière des structures tribales
everyone is armed, and therefore
tout le monde est armé et donc la
security is ensured by your tribe.
sécurité est assurée par votre tribu et
So the colonizer who arrives can
donc le colonisateur qui arrive il peut
be either an ally or an enemy.  But in
être soit l'allié soit l'ennemi mais en
any case, alliances
toute état de cause les alliances
vary. There was an Afghan warlord
varient il y avait un chef de guerre AF
who said something I
qui disait une phrase que je trouve
still find wonderful: "You can't
toujours merveilleuse qui disait on ne
buy an
peut pas acheter un chef de guerre
Afghan warlord, but you can rent him." It's a
afghan mais on peut le louer ce qui est
fantastic saying. It means
formidable comme phrase ça veut dire que
you're in an alliance system where
vous êtes dans un système d'alliance où
your allies and
chaque jour se négocient vos alliés et
enemies are negotiated daily. Somalia is the same. So why was the
vos ennemis Somalie pareil donc pourquoi
case of Somalia a caricature?
le cas de la Somalie étaitil caricatural
This country, reconstituted in the
ce pays qui a été reconstitué dans les
1950s by joining
années 50 par jonction de la Somalie
Italian and British Somaliland,
italienne et de la Somalie britannique
is a country where there was
est un pays donc où dans lequel
immediately a
immédiatement il y a eu un coup d'État
military coup. Siad Baré ruled Somalia for 50 years,
militaire siadbé et siadbé a géré 50 ans
using all the means
la Somalie en utilisant tous les moyens
of public force to repress
de la force publique pour réprimer les
ethnic identities. This means that
identités ethniques bon ça veut dire que
for the Somalis who had managed to get
pour les Somaliens qui avaient réussi à
rid of Siad Baré, their only
se débarrasser de Siad Baré leur seul
objective was to avoid a
objectif c'était surtout pas d'état
central state. Because if you put a
central parce que si vous mettez un état
central state in place, it means it will have the
central ça veut dire qu'il aura les
means of force and therefore will
moyens de la force et donc il va avoir
behave the same way as Siad
le même type de comportement que SIAT
Baré. And so we arrived at...  The
Baré et donc nous on est arrivé en
white knight, saying we'll
chevalier blanc en disant on va vous
help you rebuild a central state, the
aider à reconstituer un état central les
guys thought, yeah, there's
types se sont dit ouais il y a un pe
always a bit of money to be made, so
toujours un peu de poignon à tirer donc
we'll go to the Aidasabeba conference.
on va aller à la conférence d'adisabeba
But fundamentally, their own logic was,
mais fondamentalement leur logi propre
how do I remain
c'était comment est-ce que je reste moi
independent in my political space? And
indépendant dans mon espace politique et
that raises a serious question: there
ça pose une question grave c'est que il
may be territories on the
peut y avoir des territoires de la
planet where there is no
planète dans lequel il y a pas d'état
central state. So, you see, it's this
central alors et donc vous voyez C cet
political obstacle that means we no
obstacle politique qui fait que on ne
longer know what to do. In this case,
sait plus faire dans ce cas-là je faire
I'll draw a parallel with
je vais faire un parallèle avec la
Libya. Libya, let's say, had six
Libye la Libye on va dire 6 se
tribes that were federated by
tribus qui éta qui avait été fédéré par
Gaddafi. After his coup, Gaddafi
cadfi après son coup d'État Kaddafi
fell, power decentralized, and the
tombe le pouvoir se décentralise les
warlords wanted access to the
chefs de guerre coup veulent avoir accès
resources under their
aux ressources qui a sous leurs
feet. We're there, and
pieds on est là-bas
it's starting to annoy the
ça commence à un peu agacer les
citizens, at least those
ressortissants en ayant du moin les
citizens with ties to or, let's
ressortissants ayant des accointances ou
say, a respectful view
ayant on va dire une vision respectueuse
of Islam, who see children being
de de l'islam voit des gamins se faire
bombed under the false pretext...  Because we were
bombarder sous le faux prétexte parce
going to Libya to
qu'on allait en Libye là-bas pour aller
save the orphan of the Great
sauver la l'orphelin du Grand
Tyrant, the war for peace, HM, this grand
tyran la guerre pour la paix HM ce grand
concept, uh, we're there now,
concept euh on est là-bas maintenant la
Syria, uh, kids from the suburbs
Syrie euh les gamins issus des banlieux
with one foot between two continents, uh,
avec un pied entre deux continents euh
look at it with skepticism,
regarde la chose de façon lubitative
except that this generation is
sauf que cette génération là est
connected to the internet and also
connectée sur Internet et aussi est
influenced by the internet and also finds,
influencée par internet et trouve aussi
uh, journalistic lies a bit
euh les mensonges journalistiques un peu
hard to swallow,
difficiles à avaler
uh, we've just received strikes
euh là on vient de recevoir des frappes
on our territory, hm, hm, we understand
sur notre territoire hm hm on comprend
that for the last 30 years,
bien que depuis les 30 dernières années
armchair geopolitics is starting to
la géopolitique de salon commence à
have repercussions, uh, on the
avoir des répercussions euh sur le
ground, the military who know about
terrain les militaires qui connaissent
overseas operations know the price of blood,
les Opex connaissent le prix du sang
yes, and French citizens are
ououis et les citoyens français
now starting to feel the price of
maintenant commencent à avoir le prix du
blood on their own soil, what do we do? Well,
sang sur leur terrain on fait quoi bah
first we stop and think,
d'abord on s'arrête et on réfléchit
as GB used to say, huh, it's still always
comme disait GB dans le temps hein c'est
useful, which isn't
quand même toujours utile ce qui est pas
the current mood, huh? The current mood, having
l'ambiance du moment hein l'ambiance du
participated in a
moment c'est pour avoir participé à un
number of television programs, is that
certain nombre de plateaux de télévision
politicians come to
les hommes politiques qui viennent
acknowledge declarations that they  They're going to do this
acte de déclarations qu'ils vont faire
now so they can say in six months, "
maintenant pour pouvoir dire dans 6 mois
I told you so." The theme is, we
je l'avais dit alors la thématique c'est
need to increase the budgets of the
il faut augmenter les budgets des
intelligence services, the police,
services de renseignement de la police
the army, and so on and so forth—
de l'armée et cetera et cetera toute
things I'm not disputing. But that's not what I call stopping and thinking.
chose que je ne discute pas mais c'est
Stopping and thinking is about understanding the connection
réfléchit s'arrêter on réfléchit c'est
between foreign policy,
entre politique extérieure problème
integration problems, relations with the
d'intégration rapport avec la communauté
Muslim community, and so on. You see what I mean? That, in
musulmane et cetera voyez ce que je
my opinion, is the real
c'est ça qui à mon avis est la véritable
means of reflection, where a smile
moyen de la réflexion ou un sourire
costs less than a bullet. That's it. Well, it's not only that. It's
coûte moins cher qu'une balle c'est ça
also
bah c'est pas seulement ça c'est aussi
the fact that, obviously, the past
le fait que bien évidemment le passé à
act of violence is legitimate.
l'acte violent est-il légitime bien
Obviously, choosing
évidemment le fait de choisir des cibles
Jewish targets is unacceptable in itself, but
Juifs en soi est inadmissible mais
what does it reflect? That's
qu'est-ce qu'il traduit al c'est ça qui
the real question. Is it a
est la vér question est-ce posez une
question you're asking yourself, or is it a question you're
question ou c'est une question que vous
asking? No, no, I'm asking myself the question,
posez non non je me pose la question à
but I'm calling on
moi-même mais j'interpelle les
French politicians, if you will. That is to say...  What we
politiques français si vous voulez
need to know at this point is what the
il faut savoir qu'est-ce qui la
psychiatric theme is, if you will,
thématique psychiatrique si vous voulez
on the theme of "they don't care" and so on, it's
sur le thème ils son'en fout et cetera
not my
c'est pas mon
problem. So, at this point, we need to
problème donc un moment où il faut
question the relationship that
s'interroger sur le rapport que la
French society has fostered in these
société française a généré chez ces
young people. Yes, so we're going to
jeunes voilà oui alors le on on on on va
broaden the scope a little, the fact of
élargir un petit peu le le le fait de
classifying terrorists as having a
qualifier les terroristes ayant une
psychiatric pathology...
pathologie psychiatrique
I find it rather far-fetched, given
euh je je trouve que c'est quand même
the operation that
fort de café au vu de l'opération qui a
was mounted. That is to say, you are
été montée c'est-à-dire que vous avez en
facing extremely well-prepared, extremely heavily armed people
face de vous des gens extrêmement bien
who practice... let's take the
armés qui pratiquent on va prendre le
case of the Hyper Cacher supermarket at Porte de
cas de l'hypercacher de vincè porte de
Vincennes... it's the same
vincè euh c'est la même technique
intimidation technique as the attacks on
d'intimidation que les attentats sur les
market squares in Iraq. That is to say, on market
place de marché en Irak c'est-à-dire
days, people come to
jour de marché les gens viennent
stock up because, well, it's
s'approvisionner parce que bah c'est
market day, there are no hypermarkets
jour de marché il y a pas d'hypermarché
there, and they strike on
là-bas et il frappent les jours de
market days to terrorize the population.
marché pour terroriser la population
Samintandé, the area is a
samintandé la zone c'est une une zone
Jewish area, or at least one with a large Jewish community,
juive du moins à forte communauté juive
where everyone lives in harmony. I
où tout le monde vit en bonne entente je
know the neighborhood very, very well. There, we
connais très très bien le quartier là là
see politicians saying they're
on voit des politiques dire ce sont des
crazy instead of having a
malades au lieu d'avoir une une
much more
perception qui est beaucoup plus
structured perspective, saying, "Look, we
structurée en disant voilà nous avons
made mistakes. The people on the other side
fait des erreurs les gens en face se
organized themselves and are now attacking, fueled by
sont organisés et viennent frapper avec
the psychosis our own violence has
la psychose que notre propre violence a
generated in them." Because we're aware of the
généré chez eux parce que le fait
caricatures of
d'avoir quelques caricatures avec des
crazy people
des des des fous cinglés qui viennent
shooting at people.
tirer sur les gens on est au courant par
However, I'm coming back to your point of view:
contre je reviens sur votre point de vue
what is
quelle est
the introspection of the
l'introspection des forces de
intelligence forces in the face of VAT-era,
renseignement face à des politiques VAT
hyper-security-driven politicians? No, I don't agree with
hypécuritaire non je moi j'adhère pas à
your question because it's not the
votre question parce que c'est pas au
intelligence service's role to question the
service de renseignement de interroger
politicians' stance. They
sur le posture des politiques eux ils
have a mandate, a mission. We'll
ont un mandat ils ont une mission on va
give them, if you want, an
leur donner si vous voulez un plan de
intelligence plan. Well, the question is,
renseignement bon la question c'est
how do we get
comment est-ce qu'il faut interpeller
politicians to engage in the
les politiques pour que ils se livre à
work you're talking about? They're the ones with
ce travail que vous évoquez c'est eux
the real power.  One
qui ont le véritable pouvoir alors on
can play one's role as an
peut jouer son rôle en tant
intellectual, one can play one's role
qu'inttellectuel on peut jouer son rôle
among colleagues in
entre collaborateurs de services
administrative services, and so on, but it's
administratifs et cetera mais il est
clear that a part of the language
évident que il y a une part du langage
is restricted when one is within the
qui est quand on est à l'intérieur
administration. You can't say to
de l'administration vous NZ pas dire à
your Minister, "Excuse me, Mr.
votre Ministre excusez-moi monsieur le
Minister of Foreign Affairs, but there are a number
ministre des Affaires étrangères mais il
of
y a un certain un nombre de de
topics for intervention that need to be addressed." No
thématiques d'interventions sur
one has
lesquelles il faut revenir personne n'a
officially regretted
fait le officiellement regretter
the military intervention in Libya, for
l'intervention militaire en Libye par
example. Remember, it was the
exemple hein rappelez-vous c'était le
best day in the world for the previous
plus beau jour du monde du précdent du
president, and then Mali became
précdent président et puis la Malie
the best day in the world for the
c'est devenu le plus beau jour du monde
current president. So we have a
de l'actuel président donc on a une
kind of triumphalism as soon as it
espèce de triomphalisme dès que ça
touches on military matters, which,
touche aux choses militaires qui obture
if you will, clouds the mind. That's what
si vous voulez l'esprit c'est ce qui
happened to us after 1918. We had the
nous est arrivé après 1918 on avait la
best army in the world; you know
meilleure armée du monde vous connaissez
the rest of the story. So this type of
la suite de l'histoire donc ce type de
reflex must be understood;
réflexe il faut le comprendre
that is to say, you have to get inside
c'est-à-dire faut se mettre dans la tête
people's heads. There isn't always time for
des gens il y a pas toujours le délai de
reflection.  So, to get back to your
la réflexion alors pour revenir à votre
question, it's true that today there has been
question c'est effectivement aujourd'hui
this kind of resistance to
pourquoi il y a-t-il eu cette espèce de
collective mobilization for freedom of expression, for
collective sur la liberté d'expression
the defense of Charlie Hebdo, and so on, and
sur la défense de Charlie et cetera et
why there have obviously been these terrorist attacks.
pourquoi il y a évidemment eu ces ces
Well, I was, following a
bon moi j'ai j'ai été à la suite d'une
conversation with Valls, the Minister of
conversation avec Vals ministre de
the Interior, remarking that it was
l'Intérieur je faisais remarquer que
surprising that there wasn't a
c'était étonnant qu'il y ait pas de
counter-radical policy
politique de contre de contre radical
in France. What I meant by that was that we
tion en France qu'est-ce que j'entendais
had
par là j'entendais par là que on avait
problems with a certain part
des problèmes avec une certaine partie
of the Muslim community, but that we
de la communauté musulmane mais que on
were always in a kind of trench warfare.
était toujours dans une espèce de guerre
One minute it was about the veil, the next it was about the burqa, then this, then that,
un coup c'était sur le la bourka après
and so on. Well, what
c'était sur si après c'était sur ça et
really struck him,
bon ce qui effectivement l'a frappé
because all of a sudden he said to himself, "Yes, it's
puisque d'un seul coup il s'est dit oui
true that it's worth thinking about this," that is to
c'est vrai que ça vaut la peine de de
say, what
réfléchir comme ça c'est-à-dire quelle
policy should we adopt? It turns
serait la politique
out that, as the policy we didn't have...
àont il se trouve que comme la politique
My
àont n'avait pas été réfléchie mon
report was published in 2016, and then the
rapport est sorti en il y a eu les
attacks happened in January. So, what was
attentats en janvier donc ce qui était
my initial reflection on Mohs became a
mon ma réflexion à Mo devient une
reflection on
réflexion sur
the aftermath. Why am I emphasizing this?
l'après pourquoi j'insiste là-dessus
Because my subject isn't
parce que justement mon sujet n'est pas
how to bring
comment est-ce qu'on fait redescendre
a transcendent being back down to earth—that is, how to bring
sur terre un transcendant c'est-à-dire
the Kashi brothers back down to earth if they
redescendre les frères Kashi si ils
were still alive. Bringing them back down to earth
étaient encore vivants pour les ramener
isn't about
c'est pas par des cours d'instruction
civics lessons. And with Coulibaly, it's certain that we could have given
civique et Coulibali c'est sûr qu'on lu
him all the
aura pu lui faire tous les cours
civics lessons he could have received; we even
d'instruction civique on lui a même
allowed him to meet the President of the
permis de rencontrer le président de la
Republic, but that's not what stopped him. So, there's
République c'est pas ça qu' l'a arrêté
a real problem,
c'est donc il y a une véritable problème
a problem with the relationship between
qui est un problème de rapport de la
French society and its
société française avec sa sa composante
Muslim component, with its
musulmane avec son organisation
administrative organization, and with its
administrative et avec sa politique
foreign policy. And it's these three
extérieure et donc c'est ces trois
aspects that interested me:
volets là qui m'ont intéressé
where do these people come from? Why did
c'est-à-dire où vont chercher pourquoi
these men reach this state of
ces types sont arrivés à cet état de
violence? What led them to this point?
violence qu'est-ce qui les a amené
Obviously, you have the
jusque là évidemment vous avez
interface.  That is to say, what is
l'interface c'est-à-dire qu'est-ce qui
happening on jihadist websites, and so on
se passe sur les sites djihadistes et
and so forth? So my point isn't
cetera et cetera et donc mon propos
to say what the
n'est pas de dire les service de
intelligence services should do, or what the police
renseignement devrait faire si la police
should do, and so on, but rather what
devrait faire ça et cetera mais mon
politicians should do. Okay, I'll
politiques doivent faire bon je vais
give you some examples that might
vous citer des exemples qui peut-être
clarify things better than my explanation.
vous é claireront mieux que mon propos
All the major Western countries
euh tous les grands pays occidentaux
today have a counter-
aujourd'hui ont une politique de contr
radicalization policy, especially the
radicalisation enfin surtout les
Europeans; it's not
Européens les Américains c'est pas leur
generally a problem for the Americans. These policies were
problème en général ces politiques sont
born after a traumatic shock: the
nées après un choc traumatique attentat
London bombings in Great Britain, the caricature
de Londres en Grande-Bretagne caricature
of Muhammad in Denmark, the death of Thomas van
de Mahomet au Danemark mort de Tho van
Gogh in the Netherlands. At that time,
Gog en en Hollande à ce moment-là les
politicians were challenged, and they
politiques ont été interpellés et ils
reacted intelligently, saying to themselves, "
ont réagi intelligemment en se disant
Ultimately, our model is in
finalement notre modèle est en
trouble, our model of integration
difficulté notre modèle d'intégration
is in trouble, so we need to think
est en difficulté donc il faut réfléchir
about how to behave so that
sur la manière de se comporter pour que
we all contribute together to
on contribue tous ensemble à la
deradicalization and
déradicalisation à la
counter-radicalization." This
contreradicalisation alors ça s'est
translated into three things: first,
traduit par trois choses première chose
a public discourse, that is to say...  He
un discours public c'est-à-dire il
designates the target because
désigne la cible par que la politique
French policy has never done this,
française n'a jamais fait hein
remember Mali, that was
rappelez-vous le Mali c'était le
international terrorism, the Central African Republic is
terrorisme international la RCA c'est le
international terrorism, well,
terrorisme international enfin il est
international terrorism is everywhere. That doesn't
partout le terrorisme international ça
mean we have to stop all
veut pas dire qu'il faut arrêter tous
the bastards and corsairs, that's
les bas et tous les les cors hein c'est
not the point. You see, we don't say
pas le sujet voyez donc on dit pas
what the target is,
quelle est la cible euh
whereas in Great Britain and the Netherlands,
alors qu'en Grande-Bretagne en Hollande
they have designated it. Why this
et ca ils ont désigné pourquoi cette
designation? Because the designation
désignation parce que la désignation
allows the
permet de faire comprendre à la
Muslim community as a whole to understand
communauté musulmane dans son ensemble
that it is not the entire community that is being targeted, but
que ce n'est pas elle qui est visée dans
a part of
sa totalité c'est une partie d'entre
it whose practices,
elle dont on dénonce les pratiques les
ideologies, and so on are being denounced. This is extremely
idéologies et cetera extrêmement
important to avoid the kind of
important pour éviter l'espèce de
unconscious stigmatization that
stigmatisation inconsciente dans
every Muslim today has the
lesquelles tout musulman aujourd'hui est
right to feel. Beyond
en droit de se sentir audelà du discours
public discourse, there is an organization, an organization
public une organisation une organisation
that generally relies on
qui en général s'appuie sur les
local authorities. Why?
collectivités locales pour pourquoi
Because the person who knows best what is
parce que le type qui sait le mieux ce
happening in their municipality is not
qui se passe dans sa commune c'est pas
the prefect, it is the mayor. The mayor has
le préfet c'est le maire le maire il a
social workers, the municipal police,
les travailleurs sociaux il a la police
the Bureau  In terms of social assistance, there's the
municipale il a le Bureau d'aide sociale
Educational Assistance Office, and so
il a le Bureau d'aide éducative et
on, and therefore there's contact with
cetera et donc il a le contact avec
the imam,
l'imam il a le contact avec
the local Muslim association, and so forth.
l'association musulmane locale et cetera
This network is an alert network, and
ce réseau là est un réseau d'alerte et
then, how to put it, the state could
ensuite le comment dire l'ét pourrait
provide resources. This means, depending on the
fournir des moyens ça veut dire selon le
case reported, if it's a
cas qui est signalé si c'est un problème
family problem that explains a
familial qui va expliquer la conversion
child's sudden conversion, well, it could be a social
brutale d'un enfant ben ça peut être un
worker, it could be an imam, it could be a
PSI ça peut être un imam ça peut être un
social worker, and so on. So the state
trava ur social et cetera donc l'état
provides resources, but it's not the state as an
fournisseur de moyens mais pas l'état
actor, which is exactly the
acteur ce qui est exactement le
opposite of what France did
contraire de ce qu'a fait la France
after last spring when the
après le printemps dernier quand les
parents of children who had gone to Syria said, "
parents d'enfants parti en Syrie ont dit
We have no one to talk to. We
mais nous n'avons pas d'interlocuteur on
saw our son become radicalized. We saw him
a vu notre fils se radicaliser on l'a vu
disappear one day. We went to the
un jour disparaître on est allé à la
prefecture, we went to the courthouse, we went to the
préfecture on est allé au tribunal on
police station, but
est allé au commissariat de police mais
nobody helped. Everyone told us, 'I
personne tout le monde nous a dit je
'm not responsible.'" The
suis pas responsable la réaction
immediate, specifically French reaction was to
immédiate spécifiquement français c'est
say, "Well, it's up to the state to take care of it."
de dire bon c'est à l'état de s'en
So the state...  In France, who is responsible
occuper donc l'état c'est qui en France
for religious affairs? It's the
sur les affaires religieuses c'est le
Ministry of the Interior, that is to say, the
ministère de l'Intérieur c'est-àdire le
Ministry of the
ministère de la police vous voyez le le
Interior and Religious Affairs, you see.
le yatusintérieur et des cultes et voilà
And so the office of religious affairs, which is
et donc le bureau des cultes qui est
precisely the normal point of contact for
justement l'interlocuteur normal de
all religions, finds itself in the
toutes les religions se retrouve dans le
same administration as the
même administration que le bureau de la
police office, or rather, the police and the
police enfin que la police et que les
domestic intelligence services. So that's not right. At some point, we have to realize that this isn't
service de renseignement intérieur donc
a
n'est pas un problème de
crime problem. Then, we entrusted
délinquence ensuite on a confié
the organization and coordination to a
l'organisation et la coordination à un
committee called the
comité qui s'appelle comité
Interministerial Committee for
interministériel de prévention de la
Crime Prevention, and we relied on the
délinquence et on s'est appuyé sur le
network of prefectures.
réseau des préfectures
So we find all the typical
donc on retrouve tous les tropismes
French biases: it's left to the state, which in
français c'est à l'état de faer ce qui à
my opinion is a mistake. It's the
mon avis est une erreur c'est au réseau
public network that should be handling it, which is a
public de s'en occuper ce qui est une
mistake. So you see why
erreur bon donc le vous voyez pourquoi
I'm positioning myself upstream. And in
je me situe en amont et et et
parallel with this, we see, for
parallèlement à ça on voit on voit par
example, Qatar and Saudi Arabia doing
exemple le Qatar l'Arabie Saoudite faire
exactly what some
exactement comme certaines organisations
humanitarian organizations do, with a green flag, providing
humanitair avec un drapeau vert fournir
funds, giving money to associations.
des crédits fournir à des associations
They're doing what you're saying,
de l'argent eux font ce que vous dites
but in the opposite direction. B: they have
mais dans l'autre sens B c'est ils ont
a local policy; they have money
une politique locale ils ont de l'argent
coming in locally to...
qui arrive localement pour des projets
Local projects allow people to
locaux ce qui permet aux gens
embrace certain theories and become
d'accaisser certaines théories et de se
radicalized. What do you think about that? So
radicaliser qu'est-ce que vous en pensez
why in
alors pourquoi en France pourquoi en
France, why don't we monitor capital flows, and
France on ne suit pas les capitaux et
why do we tolerate this
pourquoi en France on tolère des
type of capital coming from the
capitaux de ce type là provenant de de
most rigorous interpretation of Islam,
la vision la plus rigoriste de l'islam
namely Saudi Arabia? And behind it all,
c'està-dire l'Arabie Saoudite et et et
we have a
derrière derrière on a une relation qui
completely schizophrenic relationship. So,
est complètement schizophrénique ou ouis
if you want to discuss the
alors alors si vous voulez sur la
question of targeting,
question de la désignation de la cible
I believe we need to
je crois qu'effectivement il faut
revisit a number of
revenir sur un certain nombre d'épisodes
extremely important historical episodes.
historiques qui sont extrêmement
Political Islam is more about the
politique c'est plutôt les Frères
Muslim Brotherhood at the beginning of the 20th century, Hassan
musulmans début du 20e siècle
al-Albani, and so on. Even if there was already
hassanelbana et cetera même si déjà il y
a kind of legitimization of the use
avait une espèce de légitimation duusage
of the audience, it doesn't matter. We're in
de l'audience peu importe on est dans
a period where this violence was
une époque où cette violence était
mainly directed against
surtout tournée contre les pouvoirs
local powers, against Mubarak, and so on.
locaux contre moubarakac et cetera et
Well, the Muslim Brotherhood made a
bon les Frères musulmans font une erreur
major mistake, in particular, by showing
majeure qui est en par particulier de se
solidarity with Saddam Hussein during
solidarité avec Saddam Hussein quand il
the war.  Kuwait, which for the
y a la guerre du Kuwait ce qui pour les
Saudis is, how shall I say, a state
Saoudiens est le comment dire le l'état
of absolute insurrection. Well,
de d'insurrection absolue bon
second point, which also
euh deuxième remarque également qui
proves, if you will, our lack
prouve si vous voulez notre insuffisance
of attention: when the Americans
d'attention quand les les les Américains
were helping the Afghan jihadists against
aidaient les les mjahidin Afghans contre
the Soviets, all American aid went through
les Soviétiques toute l'aide américaine
Saudi Arabia and the
l'Arabie Saoudite et par l'intermédiaire
Pakistani intelligence services. We didn't look into it, but
pakistanais on ne regardait pas ass mais
we reported it, but nobody wanted to give it importance. That
ça on le signalait mais personne voulait
all this
y accorderimportance que toute cette
aid went instead to the most
aide allait plutôt aux partis les plus
radical factions of the Afghan jihadists, the "
radicaux des des mjahidines Afghans
ghoudun-dun-matyar." The point is that giving
gouboudin matiar c'est que l'i donner
money to the most radical,
donner l'argent aux plus radicaux
absolutely systematically, meant they were
absolument systématiquement ils étaient
better equipped because, obviously, on
mieux dotés parce qui évidemment sur
their own turf, their donations
leur terrain de leur don sur le terrain
gave them an advantage, and so on. And the
leur donner avantage et cetera et
second aspect, which we also haven't focused on,
deuxième aspect sur lesquel on sa'est
is that the
pas non plus attarder c'est que les
Saudis stipulated that the
Saoudiens ont mis comme condition que
entire dominant doctrinal school in
toute l'école doctrinale dominante au
Pakistan, which was
Pakistan qu'il est anéphite qui était
rather, let's say, not tolerant, but rather
plutôt une disons pas tolérante mais
more open, shifted towards
enfin disons plus ouverte bascule dans
Islamism.  which is the
l'embalisme qui est l'idéologie
dominant ideology of Saudi Arabia, and we
dominante de l'Arabie Saoudite et on a
saw the Taliban on the ground 10 years later, that is to
vu 10 ans plus tard les talibans sur le
say, the
terrain c'est-à-dire les les étudiants
theology students, and so this by-product
en théologie et donc ce sous-produit
that we thought was a kind of
qu'on croyait est une espèce
outgrowth, an abscess, we didn't really know,
d'excroissance un absé on savait pas
no, it's the result of a
trop bien non c'est le résultat d'une
strategy, a strategy in
stratégie qui est une stratégie dans
which we reasoned in binary terms: the
laquelle on raisonnait en binaire les
enemy of our enemy is our friend,
ennemis de nos ennemis sont nos amis
so Saudi Arabia being against it, it's
donc l'Arabie Saoudite étant contre la
a friend. But in fact,
c'est un ami or en fait l'Arabie
Saudi Arabia had its own strategy, and the
Saoudite avait sa propre stratégie et
same remark about what you're
même remarque à propos de ce que vous
saying, that is to say, from the
dites c'est-à-dire à partir des années
80s, 80s, 90s, the Saudis, considering that it was
80 80 90 les Saoudiens considérant que
necessary to provide imams in the
il faut fournir des imams dans les
mosques of France since the
mosquées de France puisque le
French government refused to
gouvernement français se refusait à
take this variable into account,
prendre en compte cette variable a
spread these imams, in Africa, in
diffusé un peu partout en Afrique en
France, in Western countries, these
France dans les pays occidentaux euh ces
imams, in this case Salafists,
imams W habit en l'occurrence salafistes
we must call them by their name, and we
il faut les nommer par leur nom et on a
let it happen completely. The only
laissé faire complètement la seule
initial reaction was, in fact,
première réaction ça a été en fait
Sarkozy one fine day  banning an imam
Sarkozi un beau jour interdisant un imam
invited to the Bourget summit for
invité pour le le sommet du Bourget pour
the annual Bourget meeting,
la rencontre annuelle du Bourget d'entré
simply because when you
mais tout simplement parce que quand on
looked at this guy's website, it was the
regardait le site de ce type c'était du
most brutal and, how can I
l'antisémitisme le plus brutal et le
say, undisguised antisemitism,
plus comment dire sans dissimulation
and that's what allowed him to
aucune et c'est ça qui lui a permis
ban this guy from coming. So what
d'interdire la venue de ce type bon donc
you're saying is also how, at a certain point,
ce que vous dites c'est aussi comment
we implement in
est-ce qu'à un moment on décline en
domestic policy barriers that we don't
politique intérieure des barrage qu'on
want to take in
ne veut pas prendre en politique
foreign policy, which is still an
extérieure ce qui est quand même une
important question. And so today, to
question importantei et donc aujourd'hui
designate the principle is to designate what
désigné la princip c'est désigner ce
Salafism is, that is to say, it's
qu'est le salafisme c'est-à-dire c'est
a totalitarian ideology, like many we saw in the
une idéologie totalitaire he comme on en
20th century, only this one
a connu plein au 20e siècle simplement
wasn't born here, it
celle-là elle est pas née chez nous elle
was born in Saudi Arabia, and when, if you
est née en Arabie Saoudite et quand on
will, if we want to defend
si vous voulez si on veut défendre
Islam as a religion of peace and
l'Islam comme religion de paix et de
tolerance, it's better not to have
tolérance vaut mieux pas avoir l'Arabie
Saudi Arabia on our side. That is to say,
Saoudite dans son camp c'est c'est dire
if Saudi Arabia is in the
que si l'Arabie Saoudite est dans le
American camp, how come? Well, yes,
camp américain comment ça se fait bah
I agree with you, but you
oui je suis d'accord avec vous mais vous
see, this yatus, the most
voyez donc ce yatus le yatus le plus
obvious yatus being the war in Iraq where we're going to
évident étant la guerre en Irak où on va
fight the Islamic State because it
combattre l'état islamique parce que il
beheads, it cuts off the hands of thieves,
décapite il coupe les mains des voleurs
it oppresses women, and it forbids
il opprime les femmes et il interdit
other religions, to go and defend
autres religions pour aller défendre
Saudi Arabia, which beheads, cuts off the
l'Arabie Saoudite qui décapite qui coupe
hands of thieves, oppresses
les mains des voleurs qui oppriment les
women, and forbids other
femmes et qui interdit les autres
religions... we could do
religion on pour on pourra faire une
another show on the subject where,
autre émission sur le sujet où
moreover, we could debate what's
d'ailleurs on pourra débattre de ce qui
happening a little bit in the string of
se passe un petit peu dans le collier de
pearls, the rosary, where there's
perle le le chapelet d'il où il y a la
American security that's starting to
sécurisation américaine qui commence
lock down the
bien à verrouiller le le énergétique
Chinese energy sector, but anyway, to discuss this, I have
chinois mais bon pour en discuter j'ai
a question concerning the aftermath. We
une question concernant le après on voit
see our government, we see
on voit notre gouvernement on voit
Bernard Cazeneuve, we see the President of
Bernard casenu on voit le président de
the Republic asking for solutions,
la République demander des des solutions
and among these solutions, we saw...
et dans ces solutions on a vu des
the French Patriot Act. So, I'll give
euh le patriotacte à la française alors
a little reminder for our
je je fais un petit rappel pour nos
listeners: the Patriot Act, with all the
auditeurs le patriotacte avec toutes les
consequences it had in the United
conséquences que ça pu avoir aux
States on civil liberties and
États-Unis sur les libertés publiques et
on the deployment of...
sur le le déploiement de la surveillance
So now we're seeing a French version of the Patriotact,
donc maintenant on voit un patriotacte à
internet surveillance that's becoming a carbon copy
sur Internet qui devient un copier-collé
of what's happening in the United States, and
de ce qui se passe aux États-Unis et on
clearly the export of the
bah clairement l'export du patriotact
American Patriotact to European territory. What do
américain sur le territoire européen
you think about
qu'est-ce que vous en pensez la
internet surveillance? Is it
surveillance d'Internet la est-ce que ça
part of
fait partie des politiques de
counter-radicalization policies? Is it
contreradicalisation est-ce que c'est
legitimate? Won't
est-ce que c'est légitime est-ce que
we, the common people, suffer
nous la la la simple plebe nous allons
collateral damage from
pas avoir des dommages collatéraux de
this short-sighted policy that's
cette politique court-termiste qui
reacting in such a symptomatic way?
réagit d'une façon symptomatique
What do you think? First, I'd
qu'est-ce que vous en pensez d'abord je
like to draw your attention to the
voudrais attirer votre attention sur le
fact that internal security policy
fait que une politique de sécurité
is culturally
intérieure est culturellement
extremely different in major
extrêmement différente selon les grandes
democracies. For example, the British have long
démocraties bon les Britanniques
considered
considérent pendant longtemps que
having an identity card an
d'avoir une carte d'identité éit une
intrusion into privacy,
intrusion dans la privacy dans la vie
and the Americans do the same,
privée bon et leses américains pareil
considering the
considérent que c'est le permis de
driver's license issued by each state to be
conduire délivré par chacun des États
the form of identification. As for us, we have
qui est la pièce d'identité pour nous la
n't considered identity cards for a long time.  that it's an intrusion into
pense pas que c'est une intrusion dans
our private lives and a control of our
notre vie privée et un contrôle de notre
security. Conversely, the British
sécurité à l'inverse les Britanniques
had installed cameras on almost
avaient installer des caméras presque
every street in London, while
dans tous les rues de Londres alors que
we were saying that cameras are
nous on se disait les caméras c'est une
unacceptable surveillance, and so on. So
surveillance inadmissible et cetera donc
each of us made part of the
chacun des deux a fait une partie du
connection, but this is to show you how
rapprochement mais c'est pour vous dire
sometimes these "rights of the
comme parfois les discours droit de
people" speeches, if you will, don't realize how... well, how they
lomiste si vous voulez se rendent pas
are
compte combien ils sont euh com ils sont
very... how to say... very relative. If you
très comment dire très relatifs si vous
like, I'll give you an example
voulez je vais vous en citer un exemple
because I like to provoke, but I was in
parce que j'aime bien provoquer mais
Sarayevo shortly after the
j'étais à sarillevo peut temps après la
end of the war. Will we have the
fin de la gure est-ce qu'on aura le
right to provoke a... of course, of course, I was in
droit de provoquer un are tour bien sûr
Sarayevo after the
bien sûr j'étais à sarayevo après le la
end of the war. The central government
fin de la guerre le gouvernement central
had to establish a kind
avait à constituer une espèce
of administration taking into account the
d'administration tenant compte de la
Serbian component, the
composante serbe de la composante
Bosnian component, the Croatian component, and so on,
bosniaque de la composante croate et
after a gigantic humanitarian catastrophe. Come out of the
cetera après une catastrophe humanitaire
office I
gigantesque sortez du bureau dans lequel
was entering, a European sexual association
j'entrais une association de sexuel
came to ask the
européen qui venait demander au
president of the new
président de la nouvelle république
Bosnian republic what the rights of
bosniaque quel est le droit des des
homosexuals are in...  In Bosnia today,
homosexuels dans en Bosnie aujourd'hui
if this law doesn't adapt to
si ce droit ne s'adapte pas au droit
European law, we will oppose your
européen nous nous opposerons à votre
entry into the European Union. Can you
entrée dans l'Union européenne vous
imagine the kind of shock this
imaginez l'espèce de choc qu'avait ce
president felt, thinking, "Wait, I have
président se disant mais attendez j'ai
200,000 displaced people for
200000 personnes déplacées pour
whom I have to make an
lesquelles il faut que je fasse des
effort, I have to find
efforts il faut que je trouve de l'aide
international humanitarian aid,
humanitaire internationale il faut que
I have to establish an administration,
je constitue une administration il faut
I have to create an armed force?" And
que je constitue une force armée et ca
you see, the thing is, I don't
vous voyez le truc c'est pas que je je
want to criticize the rights of
veuille critiquer le droit des
homosexuals, but there has to be a
homosexuels mais il doit y avoir une
hierarchy that corresponds, on
hiérarchie qui correspond quand même sur
the issue of security as well as on the
la question de sécurité comme sur les
issue of human rights, to the
questions de droits de l'homme aux
priorities that are the
priorités qui sont les priorités
urgent priorities. So, in the case of the
d'urgence donc sur le cas de la du
Patriot Act, there are two parts to the
Patriote acte il y a deux volets dans le
Patriot Act. There's a domestic part,
Patriot Act il y a une partie intérieure
which is obviously a part where I do
qui évidemment est une partie où j'ai
n't get the impression that the Americans
pas l'impression que les Américains se
feel particularly monitored,
sentent particulièrement surveillés hein
because
parce que
otherwise, the Americans would be...
sinon les Américains été cortiqués non
wait, no, no, but there are two things
attendez non non mais il y a deux choses
precisely, and that's why I
justement et c'est pour ça que je
want to emphasize this. And then there's
voudrais insister là-dessus et puis il y
a part...  Internationally, and it was the
a une partie internationale et c'est la
international aspect that was the most
partie internationale qui était la plus
restrictive because, for example, the
contraignante parce que par exemple
Patriot Act mandated that all
patriote Act imposé que tout le trafic
container traffic, which was
de container qui était celui par lequel
thought to be the primary means of transporting
on pensait qu'arriveraiit toutes les
threats to American territory, be subject to the
menaces sur le territoire américain soit
most rigorous control. This
le plus contrôlé ça s'est traduit
translated into the fact that
comment ça s'est traduit par le fait que
the
les
Americans limited the number of
Américains limitent le nombre de ports
international ports authorized to
internationaux qui avaent le droit de
load containers bound for the United States.
charger des containerss partant vers les
For France, only one
États-Unis bon pour la France il y a un
port was authorized to do this:
seul port qui a été autorisé à faire ça
Le Havre, and with the presence of
c'est le Havre et avec présence de
American customs officials on site. For
doiniers américains sur place par
example, a second example was the
exemple deuxième exemple la liste des
passenger list with their descriptions,
passagers avec leur description leur
geography, and so on, for
gographie et cetera c'est dans des
planes arriving in the United States. So, the
avions arrivant aux États-Unis donc la
most scandalous aspect of the Patriot Act
partie patriote acte qui était la plus
was the constraints
scandaleuse c'était les contraintes
imposed on others, particularly regarding
qu'on imposait aux autres en particulier
all banking financial data.
les toutes les données financières
Every time there was a
bancaires à chaque fois qu'il y avait un
transfer of money to the United States,
transfert d'argent vers les États-Unis
the foreign bank had to
il fallait que la banque étrangère
report the origin of the money, who
signale d'où venait l'argent qui était
the owner was, and so on. And obviously, there was
le propriétaire et cetera et évidemment
no exchange of information.  The
il y avait pas d'échange d'information
Patriot Act was a fantastic way,
donc le patrio Act a été une formidable
if you will, to capture
captation si vous voulez au bénéfice des
a large portion of
États-Unis d'une grande partie des
international data for the benefit of the United States. In the
données internationales dans le patriote
French Patriot Act, I doubt we'd be able to
acte à la française je doute qu'on soit
impose the same
en mesure d'imposer les mêmes
constraints on our partners, so we're
contraintes à nos partenaires donc on
only focused on the domestic aspect. You see,
est uniquement sur le volet intérieur
it's important, as they say, the
voyez c'est important comme dis vol le
juicy part is the
volet croustillant c'est le volet
juicy domestic aspect, indeed.
intérieur croustillant effectivement bon
That said, if you break it down,
cela dit si vous le décomposez par
internet surveillance
morceau la surveillance sur Internet
is what we do in the fight
c'est ce qu'on fait en matière de lutte
against pedophilia, for example.
contre la pédophilie par exemple qu'on
I can ask you a
va faire jeux je peux vous poser une
quick question: what do you know about
petite question là vous y connaissez
fighting pedophilia online?
quoi en lutte sur internet en terme de
Because, to be honest, we
pédophilie parce que à vrai dire nous
're a network of hackers, yeah, yeah, and we
sommes une chaîne de hackur ouais ouais
hunt down pedophiles
et et les pédophiles on les traque à
day and night, and we
longueur de journée de nuit et on les
find them, especially without making baseless accusations.
trouve surtout sans lancer d'accusation
We find them mainly in
dans le vent on les trouve surtout dans
environments where there's money,
dans des milieux où il y a de l'argent
where there's a network, and when we try to flush
où il y a du réseau et quand on essaie
them out, we encounter a
un petit peu de les sortir du bois on a
lot of resistance. So,
beaucoup de boucliers qui se lèvent donc
the attraction of the internet regarding
l'attrac sur internet concernant le de
packet inspection...  All these
packet inspection tout ce qui est ce
kinds of measures, uh, no, no,
genre de mesures
but wait, let me
euh non non mais attendez moi je me
focus on the legislative aspect, okay? It's
place sur le plan législatif d'accord
not about the effectiveness of the system, the
c'est pas sur l'efficacité du dispositif
fact that we monitor the internet, just like we
le fait qu'on surveille internet comme
abuse, how should I
d'ailleurs on fasse des abus de comment
say, press law after the
dire de droit de la presse après la loi
1881 law, the adaptations we've made
1881 les adaptations qu'on a fait
successively, and so on. I don't
successivement et cetera moi j'ai pas le
feel, if you will, that our
sentiment si vous voulez que nos
freedoms are threatened when we take
libertés sont menacées quand on prend
measures against racism, against
des mesures contre le racisme contre
incitement to racial hatred, and
l'incitation à la haine raciale et
so on on the internet. It's a medium
cetera sur Internet c'est un média que
you know better than I do, but it's
vous connaissez mieux que moi mais c'est
a medium that we can
un média sur lequel on peut
imagine, at least, being limited by a
imaginer en tout cas de borné par un
certain number of legislative practices.
certain nombre de pratiques législatives
Then, that these practices are
ensuite que ces pratiques soient
effective, applicable, and so on. What do
efficaces applicables et cetera ça je
you think about the fact that it's
qu'est-ce que vous pensez du fait que ce
not controlled by a judge? Oh, well, no, no,
soit pas contrôlé par un juge ah ben non
wait, we're not going to talk about the
non attendez on va pas parler du
legislative framework that hasn't been
dispositif législatif qui n'est pas
adopted yet, but you see that regarding
encore adopté mais vous voyez que sur
wiretapping, the problem is the
les écoutes problèm la loi de
military programming law has passed,
programmation militaire est passée
Article 20 has passed, uh,
l'article 20 est passé
we're at the point of accumulating
euh on en est à faire de l'accumulation
data.  Of people with
de Data de de personnes avec des
predictive software behind them, uh, you
logiciels prédictifs derrière euh vous
as a citizen, what does that matter to
en tant que citoyen qu'est-ce que ça
you? Does it concern you? Doesn't it concern
peut vous faire ça ça vous interpelle ça
you? If I tell you, for
vous interpelle pas si je vous dis par
example, that for €2.50 I have access to my
exemple pour 2,50 € j'ai accès à mon
voter registration file, and on my
fichier de carte électorale et sur mon
voter registration file I know the
fichier de carte électorale je sais le
place of birth, that is to say, I
lieu de naissance h c'est-à-dire que je
am able to locate, for example,
suis capable de localiser par exemple
all the Moroccans in my city, and indeed
tous les marocains dans ma ville et
all the Moroccans who
d'ailleurs tous les Marocains qui
earn more money than the
gagnent de l'argent plus que la
community. That is to say, if I see a
communauté c'est-à-dire que si je vois
place of birth called "Parakeche" in the nice
lieu de naissance parakeche dans le beau
neighborhood of my city, I know that this
quartier de ma ville je sais que ce
Moroccan has made a little more
Marocain là soit est a fait un peu plus
money than the others. If,
d'argent que les autres si du jour au
overnight, I want to do the same thing
lendemain je veux faire la même chose
on Jews, on homosexuals, on
sur les Juifs sur les homosexuels sur
Black people, on people with white hair
les noirs sur les gens à cheveux blancs
in a red tie who blow their nose, I can do it
avec une cravate rouge qui se mouche je
in 48 hours maximum, I would say
le fais en 48 he grand maximum je dirais
24. What does that matter to you? Yes,
24 vous vous qu'est-ce que ça peut oui
but is it the internet itself
mais est-ce que c'est internet lui-même
or is it the
ou est-ce que c'est la
law that  The National Assembly is about to vote on what
loi que s'apprête à voter Assemblée
allows this, that's my
nationale qui permet ça c'est ça ma
question: is it the tool or the
question est-ce que c'est l'outil ou le
vector? Yes, that's the
vecteur c'est ça B oui c'est ça la
question. The fact that the internet is now such a
question que Internet soit aujourd'hui
powerful tool for penetrating
une formidable outil de pénétration dans
people's private lives, because by cross-
la vie privée des gens parce que en
referencing a number of files, not
recoupant un certain nombre de fichiers
all of which are state-owned of
qui ne sont pas tous d'origine étatique
course, this possibility of access... this is
bien sûr cette possibilité d'accès c'est
a question that concerns you as much as
une question qui vous concerne autant
the legislator. So, as a
que le législateur alors vous en tant
citizen, yeah, what do you
que citoyen ouais qu'est-ce que vous
think about giving razor blades to
pensez de donner des lames de rasoir à
a monkey? I mean, the
un singe c'est-à-dire que la la la
economic situation, the
situation économique les tensions
economic tensions are very significant.
économiques sont très importantes les
Governments change, but the
les gouvernements changent mais les
tools remain. You're talking about
outils restent les outils vous parlez
legislative tools,
des outils législatifs les outils
legislative tools? No, but precisely, the debate
législatifs non mais justement le débat
today is about adapting
aujourd'hui il est sur l'adaptation de
the legislative tool. So, that's an
l'outil législatif bon donc ça c'est un
important point. What interests me
point important moi ce qui m'intéresse
more on strategic issues
plus sur les questions stratégiques
is how,
c'est comment
excuse me, how, are we
pardon comment est-ce que aujourd'hui on
going to complain today about the fact that there is
va se plaindre du fait qu'il y a une
cyber interference from the Chinese or
ingérance informatique des Chinois ou
the North Koreans?  As revealed
des Nord-Coréens alors qu'on a révél
by the Assange case, the most
avec l'affaire àange que le plus
formidable tool for eavesdropping and
formidable instrument d'écoute et de
computer penetration was American—that is,
pénétration informatique était américain
our main ally. So
c'està-dire notre principal allié donc
my question, as a
ma question à moi en tant que
strategist, is how it is that
stratégiste c'est de me dire comment
a debate, which seems
éteindre un débat qui me paraît
essential to me, is extinguished at one point to give rise to another,
essentiel pour en faire naître un autre
which seems much less important.
qui me paraît beaucoup moins important
So your question is indeed that:
donc votre question c'est effectivement
who is currently capable
ça c'est aujourd'hui qui est en mesure
of exercising a certain
de pratiquer une certaine régulation
democratic regulation on the internet? Is it
démocratique sur Internet est-ce que
the legislator or is it
c'est le législateur ou est-ce que c'est
the hackers? We saw with Anonymous that it's more often the hackers.
les hackurs on l' bien vu avec Anonymous
This is still
que c'est plutôt les hackur ça c'est
a formidable political challenge.
quand même un défi politique formidable
We can clearly see that with Assange, today
on voit bien qu'avec Assange aujourd'hui
he is more persecuted than Abu
Assange il est plus persécuté que
al-Da'd or Abu Hamza, who
l'était abouatada ou Abou Hamza qui
were the instigators of the Londonistan
étaient les générateurs du Londonistan
of Illes.
d'Illes
How can we explain that we have
comment exp qu'on est qu'on a une
surveillance on H,
surveillance sur H
really the sock, while the
vraiment la chaussette que que les
Kashi brothers were left to roam free?
frères Kashi é était laissé dans la
No, that is to say, for
nature non c'està dire que là pour pour
Assange, well...  Surveillance has become
Assange bon la surveillance est devenue
physical, meaning that today they
physique c'està-dire qu'aujourd'hui on
simply prevent him from going out, which
l'empêche tout simplement de sortir ce
is still... What's
qui est quand même ce qui est
interesting is that... there's
intéressant c'est que on peut moi il y a
a topic that really amused me:
un sujet qui m'a beaucoup amusé c'est
why do we describe
pourquoi est-ce qu'on qualifie
the same events differently? Well, if you
différemment les mêmes faits bon si vous
want, a guy is kidnapped in Colombia
voulez un type est enlevé en Colombie
with a ransom demand, it's a
ave demande de rançon c'est un une prise
kidnapping; he's kidnapped in Iraq, it's
de un kidnapping il est enlevé en Irak
a hostage-taking; he's detained at
c'est une prise d'otage il est détenu à
Guantanamo, it's a denial of rights, you
guantanam c'est un dénis de droit vous
see what I mean? And the same applies to the
voyez ce que je veux dire et les même
same situations: he doesn't have the
c'est les mêmes situations il a pas le
right to a lawyer, he doesn't have the right to see
droit d'avocat il a pas le droit de voir
his family, he doesn't have the right to appear
sa famille il pas le droit de passer
before a judge, and so on. Yet we don't describe the
devant un juge et cetera or on qualifie
same things with the same terms. That's
pas les mêmes choses des mêmes termes ça
extremely important. Now, in
c'est un truc extrêmement important or à
Sange, that's what seems most
Sange c'est ça qui me paraît le plus
extraordinary to me: without saying it
extraordinaire c'est que sans le dire
exactly, you sense a
exactement on sent qu'il y a une
major destabilization of
déstabilisation majeure des systèmes de
surveillance systems in democratic countries
surveillance dans les pays démocratiques
because he revealed something that
parce que il a révélé quelque chose qui
was much more important than that.  that
était beaucoup plus important que ce que
the emirs of Londonistan were spreading,
propageaient les émires du Londonistan
and it's truly extraordinary
et ça c'est quand même extraordinaire
that there isn't a mobilization to
qu'il n'y ait pas une mobilisation pour
defend Assange by saying, "Wait
défendre à Sange en disant mais attendez
until Sweden commits not to
que la Suède s'engage à ne pas
extradite him to the United States, since that's what
l'extrader vers les États-Unis puisque
he's afraid of. Once
c'est ça dont il a peur parce qu'une
he's in the United States, he'll be
fois qu'il sera aux États-Unis sera
sentenced to 135 years in prison, and there's
condamné à 135 ans de prison et il y a
little chance he'll actually get out after
peu de chance qu'il sorte effectivement
those 135 years." That's what's
au bout de ces 135 ans de prisons c'est
most extraordinary: that
ça qui est le plus extraordinaire
democratic states
c'est-à-dire que des états démocratique
today don't oppose
aujourd'hui ne n'oppos pas à
Assange's extradition, for example. There are
l'extradition de Assange par exemple a
double standards. Oh yes, a
deux poids de mesure ah oui exemple
typical example: the guys from Londonistan,
caractéristique les types du Londonistan
all those emirs who orchestrated the
tous ces émires qui ont généré les
2004 attacks. England refused
attentats de 2004 l'Angleterre refusait
to extradite them to their countries of origin,
de les extrader vers leur pays d'origine
Yemen, Jordan, and so on, because
le Yémen la Jordanie et cetera parce
they said they risked the
qu'il disait qu'il risquait la peine de
death penalty. Fantastic! Yet we cooperate with the
mort formidable or on coopér avec les
United States, which applies the death penalty.
États-Unis qui applique la peine de mort
You agree?  Finally, without meaning to be mistaken, that's what I saw.
vous êtes d'accord enfin sansreur de ma
So you see how they handle this kind
donc voyez bien comment on fait de POS
of measure. His name was
de mesure le comment il s'appelait
Rachid Ramda, whom they asked
Rachid Ramda qu'on a demandé en
England to extradite following the
Angleterre d'extrader à la suite des
1994 attacks in the streets of Paris.
94 dans les rues de Paris les anglais
For ten years, the British explained that it was a
pendant 10 ans ont expliqué que c'était
complex situation, that they had to appeal to the High
comp exp qu'il fallait saisir la haut
Court, and so on. Then, of course,
cours et cetera puis évidemment les
Ramda's lawyers used every
avocats de Ramda utilisaient toutes les
legal resource. The last
ressources de droit la dernière des
refusal of extradition was explained by
refus d'extradition était expliqué par
the fact that he risked being tortured
le fait qu'il risquait d'être torturé
in French police stations. You see what
dans les commissariats français voyz ce
I mean? I've never heard the
que je veux dire j'ai jamais entendu la
British justice system say that Assange
justice britannique dire Assange il
risks being tortured in the United States.
risque d'être torturé aux États-Unis
So we're really in a system of
donc on est vraiment dans un système de
double standards. And why is
deux poids de mesure et pourquoi est-ce
Assange such a, how shall I
qu'Assange est un personnage aussi
say, disturbing figure? This reveals
dire inquiétant c'est pas ce qui révèle
practices that also
des pratiques qui sont les pratiques
exist in
également existant également dans les
democratic states where they refuse to
États démocratiques où on se refuse à
demonstrate that the United States could
démontrer que les États-Unis puissent
be a risk, or even a threat, to
être un risque voire une menace pour les
other Western countries.
autres pays occidentaux rivalité
Economic rivalry, knowledge about  The fact that
économique connaissance sur les les
political leaders listen to Angela
leaders politiques l'écoute de Angela
Merkel is quite something; one doesn't get
Merkel c'est quand même pas mal on n pas
the impression that they
l'impression que sur la vie sexuel
intend to monitor Angela Merkel's sex life.
d'Angela Merkel qui l'intention de
It's obviously the
surveiller c'est évidemment les
decision-making processes; that's what
processus décisionnels c'est ce qui se
happens in Europe, the European Commission,
passe en Europe la Commission européenne
and so on.  In the realm
et cetera donc il y avait dans le champ
of listening, there was all the means to
de l'écoute la totalité des moyens d'une
master the
maîtrise du
world, which opened the debate.
monde qui a ouvert le le débat
Germany, because they listened to their
l'Allemagne parce qu'on écoutéit son
chancellor, it's a lack of
chancelier c'est c'est un manque de
courage, what is it? It's a
courage c'est quoi c'est c'est une
resignation, it's the
démission c'est c'est on pas c'est le
power of indecision, what is it? I don't know,
pouvoir de la non décision c'est quoi je
I honestly don't know,
sais pas je sais pas franchement je sais
but it's true that it's a
pas mais c'est vrai que c'est une
cowardice that is still unacceptable.
veulerie qui est quand même inadmissible
Unacceptable is the term, the way. And
inadmissible c'est le terme la veie et
so, since we have all these means,
donc puisqu'on a tous ces moyens
since we have all these means, we
là puisqu'on a tous ces moyens là on
can therefore ultimately have an attitude,
peut donc finalement avoir une attitude
if we can, and if we don't,
si on peut et qu'on fait pas
at the level of semiotics, what does that
au niveau de la la sémiologie qu'est-ce
indicate? I think it's a
indique je pense que c'est une réflexion
very short-term strategic reflection, which is:
stratégique à très court terme qui est
we don't get angry with the major ally, it's
on ne se fâche pas avec le grand allié
very short-term strategy.
c'est de la stratégie à très court terme
I was very interested, for
moi je me suis beaucoup intéressé par
example, in how, if you
exemple au à la façon dont si vous
will, General de Gaulle conceived his
voulez le général de Gaul penser sa
diplomatic strategy of rupture.
stratégie diplomatique de rupture
That is to say, one fine day he said to his
c'est-à-dire un beau jour il dit à ses
collaborators, "I'm going to recognize the People's Republic of China."
collaborateurs je vais reconnaître la
Just imagine,
Chine populaire pensez bien qu'autour de
everyone around him was saying, "General, you ca
lui tout le monde a dire général vous
n't be serious, the People's Republic of China, the
n'y pensez la Chine populaire des
Americans!" And he said, "We're going to
Américains et C euh il a dit on va se
withdraw from the UT." You can imagine,
retirer de l'UT temp vous pensez bien
people around him were saying, "
qu'autour de lui les gens lui ont dit
Well, in the heat of the moment, he had
bon dans la foulée il a fait rapatrier
the URE repatriated from France." And there you have it. So, if you
l'URE de la France et voilà donc si vous
want, you have a
voulez vous avez autour de vous un
certain number of people around you. You have to understand
certain nombre de gens il faut connaître
the sociology of ministerial offices. If you
la sociologie des cabinets si vous
want, an office surrounding a
voulez un cabinet qui entoure un
minister is like a court surrounding a
ministre c'est une cour qui entoure un
king, and the court is composed of courtiers, right?
roi et le cour est composé de courtisans
And so, when you have
hein bon et donc vous avez quand vous
people around you who, all
avez autour de vous des gens qui toute
their lives, say, "Ah yes, Mr.
leur vie disent ah oui monsieur le
Minister, you're right." Well, for
ministre vous avez raison enfin pendant
the two years you're in power, yes,
les 2 ans vous êtes au pouvoir oui
Mr. Minister, you're right, Mr.
monsieur le ministre avez raison
Minister, what a good idea,
monsieur le ministre quelle bonne idée
Mr. Minister! There comes a point when
monsieur ministre il y a un moment où
you disconnect from reality. The
vous déconnectez avec la réalité la
greatness of Degol was to always have
grandeur degol c'était d'avoir toujours
that reality, that contact
cette réalité avec la cette ce contact
with the reality of
avec la réalité de la géopolitique du
world geopolitics. Well, today, and I  I know he really put himself on the line, right? Well,
monde bon aujourd'hui et je sais qu'il
today we're in a
hein bon aujourd'hui on est dans une
generation, like mine, where, if
génération à laquelle j'appartiens où si
you want to know the world,
vous voulez la connaissance du monde
when you're in the upper echelons of
quand on est dans les haut sphères de
decision-making, it's very simple: you arrive
décision c'est très simple vous arrivez
in a foreign country, the
dans un pays étranger la voiture de
ambassador's car is waiting for you, takes you to the
l'ambassadeur vous attend vous emmène à
embassy, ​​and at the embassy you have
l'ambassade à l'ambassade vous avez un
lunch where the ambassador explains
déjeuner où l'ambassadeur vous explique
the country to you in two hours. Then you have your
le pays en 2hes ensuite vous avez vos
official meetings where you see your counterparts who, of course,
entretiens officiels où vous voyez vosom
tell you everyone
qui évidemment vous disent tout le monde
attaches great importance to
accorde beaucoup d'importance à la
France's position on the issue that
position de la France sur le sujet qui
concerns us, and so on. What is
nous préoccupe et cetera quelle est
your analysis? In the evening you have an
votre analyse le soir vous avez un dîner
official dinner. The next day you have
officiel le lendemain vous avez à
further contact with your
nouveau des contacts avec votre vos
counterparts, and then you get back on
homologues et puis vous remontez dans
the plane. Okay, so a little Champagne and a
l'avion bon alors petit en Champagne et
pat on the back, yes, that's it, but above all, what kind of
tapage sur l'épaule oui c'est ça mais
contact do you have?
c'est surtout quel contact avez-vous
Imagine you're going to Israel, going to
imaginez-vous que vous alliez en Israël
Viva, only you see what
en allant àel à viv seulement vous voyez
I mean, and you're going to New
ce que je veux dire et vous allez à New
Delhi, being... what if you're going to Canada?
Delhi en étant qu' vous allez enant can
You're going to the United States, going to...
da vous allez aux États-Unis en allant à
Washington, suddenly you discover that
Washington coup vous découvrez qu' un
racism exists in the United States,
racisme aux États-Unis qui se traduit en
particularly in the fact that
particulier par le fait qu'on peut buter
Black people can be killed in the street. I'll just
des Noirs dans la rue je vais juste
digress for a moment: the chain of
ouvrir une parenthèse la chaîne de
command within the
commandement au niveau des services de
intelligence services, there are indeed honorable
renseignement il y a bien des honorables
contributors on the ground
contributeurs qui sont sur le terrain
who gather information.
qu' font remonter de l'information je
Take, for example, the
prends par exemple les révolutions
Arab Spring. You were talking about an
arabes vous parliez deune officine de
economic intelligence agency, not a
d'intelligence économique par pas
business agency. Thank you, excuse me, that's a
officine entreprise merci excusez-moi ça
derogatory term. That was
c'est le qualificatif dégradant c'est
n't the function, sorry,
c'était pas la fonction désolé
excuse me. There are people on the
excusez-moi euh il y a des gens de
ground who gather information,
terrain qui font monter de l'info des
people who are connected to the
gens qui sont connectés avec la
population, people who walk around, who go and gather information
population des gens qui se baladent qui
to find out what's happening,
de bergers pour savoir ce qui se passe
if there have been guys with
sil a eu des mecs passés avec des
Kalashnikovs. There are people who do that,
Kalashnikovs il y a des gens qui font ça
there are people who gather
il y a des gens qui font monter de
information. These people are starting to
l'information ces gens-là commencent à
loosen their grip a bit, meaning that the
ranger un peu leur frein c'estàd que la
chain of command, the flow of information...
chaîne de commandement la remontée
Information isn't being respected. What do
d'information n'est pas respecté
you think about all this?
qu'est-ce que vous en pensez de tout ça
Listen, I'm going to tell you about an episode
écoutez je vais vous raconter un épisode
that was recounted to me because I became
qu'on m'a relaté parce que je me suis
very interested in the reasons, how to
beaucoup intéressé à la raison comment
put it, at the beginning of the Franco-
dire au début de la relation Fran
Iranian relationship after the 1979 Revolution.
iranienne après la Révolution 79
Remember, Romelu Lumpur was in France when he
rappelez-vous Romé é tant en France il
came back on an Air France plane. There was
revient dans un avion d'Air France il y
this extraordinary demonstration with
a cette extraordinaire manifestation o
3 million Iranians in the streets,
il a 3 millions d'Iraniens dans la rue
and so on. They were applauding, along with
et cetera il éit qui applaudissent avec
the captain, who was making
le commandant de bord qui fait des
announcements about CETA. So, a kind of
centresomé et CETA donc une espèce
love affair where every day in
d'histoire d'amour où tous les jours
front of the French embassy there were
devant l'ambassade de France il y avait
white flags, and so on. Well, and then,
des glauls blancs et cetera bon et puis
in a few months, we found ourselves alongside
en peu de mois on se retrouve au côté de
Saddam Hussein and we were
Saddam Hussein et on est le principal
Saddam Hussein's main supplier. So, what happened
fournisseur de Saddam Hussein donc
between the
qu'est-ce qui s'est passé entre les
two? And while talking with someone who
deux et en discutant avec quelqu'un qui
was in the ministerial offices at that time,
était à ce moment-là dans les cabinets
he told me, "Listen, I
ministériel il me dit écoute moi je suis
arrived in Iran in '78, something like
arrivé en Iran en 78 quelque chose comme
that,
ça
'79. My ambassador..."  He left his post, and
79 mon ambassadeur quittit son poste et
the head of the GSE (General Security Service) post left his
le chef de poste des GSE quittit son
post. The ambassador wrote his will, his
poste l'ambassadeur le fait son
letter, if you
testament qu'il fait sa lettre si vous
will, in which he explained the
voulez dans lesqueles il explique les
conclusions he drew from his stay in
conclusions qui tirent de son séjour en
Iran, and in which he said, "The
Iran et dans lequel il dit le chat
Iranian cat seemed to me a visionary
d'Iran m'a paraaraît un ses visionnaire
head of state, a visionary to whom the brightest
chef d'État visionnaire auquel le plus
future is promised," and so on. Two months
bel avenir est promis et cetera 2 mois
after the
après la
Revolution, the head of the GSE post said, "
Révolution le chef de poste des GSE dit
Iran is a country where
l'Iran c'est un pays dans lequel il y a
1% are French-speaking—those are the ones we see
1 % de francophone c'est ceux qu'on voit
all the time—2% are English-speaking—that's what we
tout le temps il y a 2 % d'anglophone
see, but a little less—and there
c'est ce qu'on voit mais un peu moins et
are 97% non-native speakers whom we
il y a 97 % de personnophon qu'on ne
never see. What happens next? That's where it gets
voit jamais qu'est-ce qui se passe après
interesting." To
c'est là que c'est intéressant pour
answer your question, he was
répondre à votre question il se fait
reprimanded by the Quai d'Orsay, who told him, "That's
allumer par le qu d'orsé qui lui dit ce
not the official line of
n'est pas la ligne officielle de la
French diplomacy." He was reprimanded
diplomatie française il se fait allumer
by his own administration, saying, "
par sa propre administration disant
Don't forget that our mission is to
n'oubliez pas que notre mission est de
provide raw intelligence." You see...  The
fournir du renseignement brut vous voyez
reason I'm citing this example is because
pourquoi je cite l'exemple c'est parce
a system's capacity to take
que la capacité d'un système à prendre
into account something that represents a break
en compte quelque chose qui une rupture
is extremely difficult. You're going to
est extrêmement difficile vous allez
explain to your minister, "Mr.
expliquer à votre ministre monsieur le
Minister, you know we're completely messing things up.
ministre vous savez on est en train de
Either you change your
complètement soit c'est vous qui changez
assignment, you disappear
de d'affectation c'est vous disparaissez
from the cabinet, or your minister is
du cabinet soit votre Ministre est
intelligent, he stops, he
intelligent il s'arrête il
listens, we do what?" But what I mean is,
écoute on fait quoi mais ce que je veux
you have both types of
dire et donc vous avez les deux types de
scenarios. You still have to realize
scénarios faut quand même se rendre
that there's a
compte que si vous voulez il y a un
factor that political scientists never
facteur que jamais les politologues
use in explaining the
n'utilisent dans le l'explication du
world: the stupidity of
monde c'est la bêtise des de
the individual. A real-life example to help you
l'individu exemple vécu pour que vous
understand: the genocide in
compreniez la chose euh génocide au
Rwanda. The genocide breaks out, the ambassador
Rwanda le génocide éclate l'ambassadeur
there talks about rumors.
sur place parle de rumeurs
Well, we saw what happened next. The fact remains that
bon on a vu la suite toujours est-il que
we find ourselves in an
on se trouve dans une situation
international situation where the Americans no
internationale où les Américains ne
longer wanted to intervene because of
voulaient plus intervenir parce qu'il y
Somalia, the Black Hawk Down affair,
avait la Somalie l'affaire faucon noir
and so on. So Clinton
et cetera donc Clinton ferme les yeux
completely turns a blind eye. The other Western countries
complètement les autres pays occidentaux
say, "Africa isn't ours."  Et
disent nous l'Afrique c'est pas nous et
cetera, and France, which had been one of the
cetera et la France qui avait été un des
countries that most supported
pays qui avait le plus soutenu à
Aburimana,
biarimana
as it was a period of—
comme c'est une période de
not collaboration, what do
de non pas de collaboration de comment
you call it—when there was a
on appelle quand il y a il y avait un
left-wing government and then a
gouvernement de gauche et puis non un
right-wing government, and then, in the middle, a
gouvernement de droite et puis mitan de
cohabitation government, pardon me, it just so happened that it was
cohabitation pardonation il se trouve
a
par chance que c'est un gouvernement de
cohabitation government, meaning that Aburimana,
cohabitation c'est-à-dire que miteran
who was the most pro-Africanist, if you
qui était le plus africaniste si vous
will, was
voulez des soutiens d'abarimana se
challenged by Baladure and Juppé,
trouve contesté par baladure et par Jupé
who absolutely wanted to prevent the
qui eux veulent absolument empêcher le
genocide from happening. So you see the
génocide de se faire donc voyez le le la
internal division within the French government.
fracture interne au gouvernement
Ultimately, Juppé and Baladure prevailed, and
finalement Jupé et baladure l'emporte et
so Operation Turquoise was put in
donc on met l'opération Turquoise en
place. Operation Turquoise consisted of
place l'opération Turquoise consistait à
trying to create secure zones
essayer de faire des zones sécurisées
so that the refugees could remain in
pour que les toutsis restent encore sur
place and be protected. I know this
place puissent être protégé je le sais
because I participated in its
parce que j'ai participé à la à sa
design. Well, it's a Sunday
conception bon on se trouve un dimanche
afternoon in the office of the chief
après-midi dans le bureau du directeur
of staff. So, in the office of the
de cabinet donc dans le bureau du
chief of staff—it was
directeur de cabinet c'était c'était
Lesutard at the time—only chiefs, with
lesutard à l'époque que des chefs avec
the characteristic, generally, of chiefs.
la caractéristique en général des chefs
That is to say, who had never set
c'est-à-dire qui n'avait jamais mis les
foot in Rwanda since, obviously, their
pieds au Rwanda puisque évidemment leur
careers were based in Paris. You did
carrière était parisienne vous quand
n't ask people, in addition to being
même pas demandé aux gens en plus d'être
on the ground, how much are
sur le terrain bon le chef de cabinet
these people paid?
milire ils sont pay combien ces gens-là
Sorry, how much are they paid? It's not very well
pardon ils sont payés combien c'est pas
paid in the administration. 5,000, 6,000?
très payé l'administration 5000 6000
What? 5,000, 5,
quoi 5000 5
6,000? No, I don't think so. I think it must
6000 non je pense pas je pense ça doit
be much less than that. For a
être beaucoup moins que ça pour un
director of central administration, it
directeur d'administration centrale ça
must be around €1,500 per month,
doit êtreentour de 1500 € par par mois
I think. Okay, I'll wait. I think I'll
je crois d'accord je attends je pense je
give you a figure like that, but
vous donne un chiffre comme ça mais bon
wait, let me think. What would that be? That would be
attendez laissez-moi réfléchir ça ferait
20,000 per year. No, it's, I
quoi ça ferait 20000 par an non c'est je
might be below that. That's something that doesn't add up.
peut-être au dessous là c'est quelque
I'll give you the
chose qui va pas je je vous donnerai les
figures, but we're not talking about
chiffres mais on n'est pas dans les dans
private sector rates, are we? And so,
les tarifs du privé hein d'ord et alors
the head of the military cabinet
donc le chef du cabinet militaire
explains the deployment of
explique le déploiement des forces
French forces who are to arrive on the ground
françaises qui doivent arriver sur place
to secure areas. He uses
pour sécuriser des zones alors il tient
a fairly simple line of reasoning, which is a
un raisonnement assez simple qui est une
military technique.  He said in Goma, in the
technique militaire il dit à Goma aux
Aïr Mountains, there's an airbase, so
Aïr il y a une plateforme aérienne donc
we'll position ourselves there and deploy
on va se mettre là et on va déployer
in northern Rwanda because it's
dans le nord du Rwanda parce que c'est
simpler in terms of communication and
plus simple en terme de communication de
troop deployment. The
déploiement des troupes et cetera la
only person in the meeting who had no
seule personne qui était dans la Réunion
reason to be there was
qui n'avait aucune raison d'y être
the only person who
c'était la seule personne qui
knew Rwanda; he was an
connaissait le Rwanda cétait un
academic whom a guy from the "
universitaire que un type du cabinet
intelligent" cabinet, in this case Jean-
intelligent qui é en l'occurrence Jean
Christophe Ruffin, had brought to the
Christophe Ruffin avait amené dans la
meeting. So this guy listened to all this;
Réunion donc ce type il écoute tout ça
nobody had much to say because
personne avait grandchose à dire parce
nobody was capable of criticizing
que personne éétait capable de critiquer
the military technicalities, and he raised his
la technicité militaire et lui il lève
hand and said, "Listen, excuse me, but
le doigt il dit écoutez excusez-moi mais
if you position yourself in northern Rwanda
si vous vous mettez au nord du Rwanda
today, there's nothing left in
aujourd'hui il y a plus tout si au
Rwanda because they've all been
Rwanda parce qu'ils ont tous été
massacred; they've taken refuge in the
massacrés ils se sont réfugiés dans les
southern hills. So if you position yourself in the
collines du Sud donc si vous vous mettez
north, you'll keep pushing to
au nord vous allez pousser pour toujours
explain that you're there to save
expliquer que vous êtes là pour sauver
the TCIS, but none of the belligerents will
des TCIS mais aucun des belligérants ne
believe what you're
croira ce que vous es en train
explaining since they already know, and so
d'expliquer puisqu'ils le savent et donc
they'll think that, once again, the
ils vont penser qu'une fois de plus les
French  They intervene because they come to
Français interviennent parce que ils
try and save the regime
viennent essayer de sauver le régime
they have always supported, the regime
qu'ils ont toujours soutenu le régime
of the... well, if this guy hadn't been
des utou bon ce type n'aurait pas été
in the room, everyone would have given
dans la salle tout le monde aurait donné
the explanation I just
l'explication que je viens de vous
gave you because we always assume that decision-
donner parce qu'on suppose toujours que
makers are rational. We're
les les décideurs sont rationnels on va
not going to explain that people don't
pas expliquer que les gens ne
know the country and therefore
connaissent pas le pays et qui donc vont
make such an important decision in
prendre une décision aussi importante en
human terms, but simply out of stupidity.
terme humain mais simplement par bêtisse
And that's terrible when you're a
et c'est c'est terrible quand vous êtes
political scientist because if you have to
politologue parce que si vous devez
take people's stupidity into account, it
prendre en compte la bêtise des gens ça
means that part of your
veut dire qu'une partie de votre
scientific rigor has disappeared, and yet that's
scientificité a disparu et c'est
an important element of the last two
pourtant un élément important de de deux
questions. It's precisely one of the things I'm going to come back to: is it through this
questions c'est justement une des choses
same stupidity that
c'est par la même bêtise en fait que
you could
vous pourriez
explain a kind of ideology that
expliquer une sorte d'idéologie à eu qui
continues to lead us into
nous qui continue de nous emmener dans
wars that are not at
des des guerres qui ne sont pas du
all, I would say, of any interest
tout jeallis dire d'un intérêt
whatsoever for the country and Europe in
quelconque pour la et l'Europe en
general? Well, I'll be more polite than
général bon je vais être plus poli que
you, let's say it's a lack of
vous disons que c'est une absence de
international culture.  He put it like
culture internationale on le dit comme
that, but basically the question is perfectly
ça h mais en gros la question est tout à
legitimate. Let's take the case of our
fait légitime prenons le cas de notre
president today. His
président aujourd'hui sa culture
international experience was about belonging to
internationale c'était d'appartenir à
the international community, going to meetings
l'international d'aller à des réunions
of the Socialist International where
de l' l'international socialiste où il y
Mbarak and Ben Ali were present. Well, that's all,
avait Mbarak et Ben Ali bon c'est tout
I've given you a quick overview.
je vous ai fait le tableau rapidement et
So this lack of
donc cette absence de culture
international experience is, in particular, the idea
internationale c'est en particulier de
that a country has a culture, a
se dire qu'un pays ça a une culture une
kind of social cohesion, a relationship to
espèce de cohésion sociale un rapport à
war, and so on, which means that
la guerre et cetera qui fait que
we can avoid
on peut ne pas s'interroger on peut
questioning the necessity of
s'interroger sur la nécessité d'utiliser
using armed means. The second
d'utiliser des moyens armés deuxième
characteristic, which is somewhat a
caractéristique qui est un peu la
consequence of the picture I painted earlier, is that there is
conséquence du tableau que j'ai dressé
no
tout à l'heure il y a pas d'ennemi
strategic enemy today, and therefore the
stratégique aujourd'hui et donc le
real decision-making criterion is
véritable critère de décision c'est
domestic public opinion. If you
l'opinion publique intérieure si vous
have a media intellectual writing
avez un intellectuel médiatique qui vous
an article about a country, saying things like "We
fait un pays un article du genre nous
are all Ukrainians" or "We
sommes tous des Ukrainiens ou nous
are all Libyans," then the
sommes tous des Libyens vous le
politician reads the newspaper in the morning when he
politique il lit le journal le matin en
arrives and thinks, "Good heavens, what should I do?"
arrivant et il se dit ciel diable que
You see what I mean?  What I mean is, it's
dois-je faire vous voyez ce que je veux
not a rational process; it's
dire c'est pas un processus rationnel
become a process of, how to
c'est devenu un processus de comment
say, geopolitics of
dire de géopolitique de
emotion. The deadliest conflict
l'émotion le conflit le plus meurtrier
since the end of World War II
depuis la fin de la Seconde Guerre
is the Congo conflict: 25,000,
mondiale c'est le conflit du Congo 25000
2.5 million dead, 25,000
2 milliion et demi de morts 25000
child soldiers, sex slaves, and so on.
enfants soldat esclav sexuel et cetera
Whoever talks about the Congo conflict, it's too
qui parle du conit du Congo c'est trop
complicated. They're Black people, we don't know, it's
compliqué c'est des noirs on sait pas
the M23, who knows, who, you see what
c'est le M23 qui sa qui vous voyez ce
I mean? So it's not the
que je veux dire c'est donc pas la
gravity of the crisis that motivates this, it's the
gravité de la crise qui motive la chose
media's perception of the
c'est la la gravité médiatique de la
crisis, and that's what's dramatic, right?
crise et c'est ça qui est dramatique
And so, instead of having a kind of "
hein et donc au lieu d'avoir une espèce
C," this grandeur of Degol, which could at
de C cette grandeur de degol qui pouvait
one point have said, "But the crisis, we
à un moment se dire mais la crise il
must take into account its
faut en tenir compte de ces
political characteristics before
caractéristiques politiques avant de
deciding," here we decide based on what
décider là on décide en fonction de ce
public opinion will think of what
que l'opinion publique va penser de ce
you are doing. Do
que vous êtes en train de faire est-ce
you think we should stay
que vous croyez que nous devrions rester
in the
dans l'
past? I don't know, you just got us
temps je pas de nous avez justement fait
out of the thing, from what he called...
sortir du machin de ce qu'il qualifia de
If you want to take us back there,
machin si vous voulez de nous y faire
the history of
retourner si vous voulez l'histoire de
NATO is quite interesting because
l'OTAN est assez intéressante parce que
when, in 1991, the USSR decided to
quand en en 91 donc l'URSS décide de
dissolve the Warsaw Pact, and in 1989,
dissoudre en 89 décide de dissoudre le
the Western powers had
Varsovie les occidentaux avaient
implicitly accepted the dissolution of
implicitement accepté la dissolution de
NATO. This didn't happen, as you've seen,
l'OTAN ça c'est pas fait comme vous avez
and above all, the
pu le constater et puis surtout les
Russians had stipulated that there should be no eastward
Russes avaient mis comme condition qui
expansion of NATO. You
d'extension de l'OTAN vers l'est vous
saw what happened next. So, we're in a
avez vu la suite donc on est dans un
system, once again, that completely disregards what the
système encore une fois qui ne tient pas
other side thinks. We'll
compte du tout de ce que pense l'autre
find them, we'll
et donc on va le trouver comme on va le
consider them threatening, unpleasant,
considérer comme menaçant désagréable
aggressive, and so on, without asking ourselves if
agressif et cetera sans se demander si
we ourselves generated this aggression,
on a nous-même généré cette agression
this spitefulness, this reaction. That's
cette méchanceté cette réaction c'est ça
the intellectual process. Why? Because
le processus intellectuel pourquoi parce
we invented something remarkable in the
qu'on a inventé un truc formidable dans
1950s, let's say,
les années dans les années 50 disons qui
called international public opinion.
s'appelle l'opinion publique
It's a remarkable
internationale c'est formidable comme
idea because every time we speak,
idée parce queà chaque fois qu'on parle
we speak in the name of international public opinion.
on parle au nom de l'opinion publique
The countries that voted for the resolution banning  The
internationale les pays qui ont voté la
airstrike on
résolution d'interdiction aérienne sur
Libya represents 9% of the
la Libye c'est 9 % de la population
world's population. The others either
mondial 9 % les autres se sont soit
abstained or voted against it, but this 9%
abstenu ont voté contre mais ces 9 %
represents international public opinion.
c'est l'opinion publique internation
So, each time, we
nation et donc à chaque fois on se
justify ourselves, if you will, by explaining
légitime si vous voulez en expliquant
that we are there because we are
que nous sommes là parce que nous sommes
the white knight, bearers of all
le chevalier blanc porteur de toutes les
universal values. That's the
valeurs universelles et ce c'est ça le
intellectual process I'm referring to. And so,
processus intellectuel j'ai et donc
the lack of international culture—that's it.
l'absence de culture internationale
Can you summarize
c'est ça est-ce que vous pouvez résumer
international opinion?
l'opinion internationale
Well, it's going to be difficult to
par alors ça va être difficile à
formulate
formuler
this in a nutshell. It's made up of
ça par une min sa forme de
people, let's say, lulled by the
gens on va dire bercé par le le jeu
Hollywood version of the White Knight, the
hollywoodien du du Cheval Blanc du
good American who comes to save the
gentil américain qui vient sauver la
little girl, with this same
petite fille avec un ce même système de
projected value system. So, it's, let's
valeur projetée donc c'est c'est on va
say, 9%—to be a bit vulgar—9% of the "bourgeois
dire 9 % pour être un peu vulgaire 9% de
bohemians" of international opinion who
Bobo de l'opinion internationale qui
vote, having the purchasing power to
vote ayant un pouvoir d'achat pouvant
influence X or Y
permettre de faire rlire X ou Y
leaders. Is this the
dirigeants est-ce que c'est est-ce que
armed wing of our politicians,
c'est le le bras armé de nos politiques
this famous international opinion that we
cette fameuse opinion internationale
can manipulate?  Corsam, we
qu'on peut manipuler corsam on les
either bombard them with anxiety-inducing rhetoric or with feel-good sentiments.
abrevons soit de de propos anxiogène euh
Listen, in any case, it raises a
voà écoutez en tout cas ça pose une
question that deserves more in-
question qui mériterait une analyse plus
depth analysis. That is to say,
approfondie c'est-à-dire
indeed, but you're right to formulate it, to
qu'effectivement mais vous avez raison
formulate the
de le formuler enfin de de formuler la
question, I have to
question euh moi je suis obligé de
note, we can clearly see that we
constater on le voit bien que on
find the same character, BHL, who
retrouve le même personnage BHL qui
starts the war in Libya and then
déclenche la guerre en Libye et puis qui
brings people back to the new
ensuite ramène les gens du le nouveau
Ukrainian power, to the
ukrainien dans le nouveau président au
new president. So there's something that
nouveau président donc il y a quelque
deserves to be
chose qui quand même mérite qu'on
questioned, but what makes
s'interroge sur mais qui fait la
these individuals so notorious? So what's
notoriété de ces individus h alors ce
interesting is that you have
qui est intéressant c'est que vous avez
a certain number of intellectuals
chez un certain nombre d'intellectuels
in positions of power. That is to say,
des positions de pouvoir c'est-à-dire
when you have the same individual who is on the
quand vous avez un même individu qui est
board of directors of Channel 7, who
au conseil de surveillance de la 7 qui
is on the World Electoral Committee, and so on
est au comité d'électeurs du monde et
and so forth. Have you seen the
cetera et cetera vous avez vu les
new Gard? Yes, yes, I saw it. What did
nouveaux cha Gard oui oui je l'ai vu ou
you think? Ah, I
qu'est-ce que vous avez pensé ah j'ai
found it very good.  REC, we
trouvé ça très bien oua vous le REC on
see it on
le constate d'ailleurs sur les plateaux
TV sets, recommend it, oh yes, yes of course,
télé recommandez ah ben oui oui bien sûr
I saw it, I found it, do
sû moi je l'ai vu j'ai trouvé ça est-ce
you know Naomi Clin, it rings a bell,
que vous connaissez Naomi clin ça me dit
the shock strategy, I don't know that, well,
quelque chose la stratégie du choc je
I
connais pas ça tiens je vous le
highly recommend it and I suggest we do another
conseille vivement et je vous propose
show on this
qu'on refasse émission sur ce sur ce
concept, one last question just to
concept une dernière question juste pour
finish on your topic, in the
terminer sur votre sujet dans la
seduction strategy you
stratégie de de séduction que vous
mentioned, that is to say, the relationship with the United
évoquiez c'est-à-dire le rapport aux
States, just two or three things so
États-Unis juste deux ou trois choses
that your listeners remember these
pour que vos auditeurs retiennent ces
things: the relationship to war,
choses en tête le rapport à la guerre
Americans lost fewer people
les Américains ont perdu moins de monde
in all the conflicts of the 20th century than
dans tous les conflits du 20e siècle que
deaths due to
de morts pour des raisons de détention
gun ownership within the United States, well,
d'armes à l'intérieur des États-Unis bon
when you have on one hand 20 million
quand vous avez d'un côté 20 millions de
deaths in Russia and you have less than
morts en Russie et que vous avez moins
a million deaths in the United States,
d'un million de morts au état États Unis
the relationship to war is not the same
le rapport à la guerre n'est pas le même
because you never refer to 39-45,
parce que vous n'z jamaisérence à 3945
yes to 39, no, no, all the wars of the
oui à 39 non non toutes les guerres du
20th century, all the wars of the
du 20e siècle he toutes les guerres du
20th century, including Vietnam, there were
20e siècle y compris le Vietnam il
148,000 deaths during World War II. There were approximately 190,000
190000 morts pendant la Seconde Guerre
American deaths and 169,000
mondiale américain et il y a eu 169000
Belgian deaths. How many Russian deaths?
morts belges combien de morts russes et
20 million. Very good. And so you
20 millions très bien bon et donc vous
have something that is
avez quelque chose qui est quelque chose
quite fascinating, that is to say, when
d'assez fascinant c'est-à-dire quand la
war has never happened on your
guerre ne s'est jamais passé sur votre
territory, when you don't know what
territoire que vous ne savez pas ce que
a bombed city is like, you don't know what
c'est qu'une ville bombardée vous savez
ration tickets are, you don't know what it's like to search for
rationnement vous savez pas ce que c'est
water sources,
que de faire des que à des points d'eau
and when your culture has always been mediated
et que votre a toujours été médiatisé
by Hollywood, your relationship to war
par Hollywood votre rapport à la guerre
and the decision to intervene armed
et à la décision de l'intervention armée
is completely different from that of the
est complètement différent de celui des
Russians. Well, I listened to an interview with
Russes bon j'ai écouté une interview de
Jean Gabin. You know that Jean Gabin
Jean Gabin vous savez que Jean Gabin
was in Hollywood at the time when
était à l'époque à Hollywood quand la
France lost the war, and that
France perd la guerre et que finalement
he finally decided to go to London to join
il décide de rejoindre Londres pour
the Free French Forces.
s'engager dans les Forces françaises
He  He did it discreetly, he didn't
libres il a fait discrètement il s'en
boast about it, he left, he went
est pas vanté il est parti il est allé
to the British consulate, he
au consulat de Grande-Bretagne il a
asked to leave for London. He
demandé à partir vers Londres il se
found himself on one of those convoys,
trouve dans un bateau de ces convois
you know, the North Atlantic ones, which
vous savez de l'Atlantique Nord qui
were under submarine fire,
était sous le feu des sous-marins des
torpedoes, submarines,
torpilles des sous-marins sous le feu
bombing raids, German action,
des bombardi alon rant d'action allemand
and so on, and he was clenching his buttocks because
et cetera et il serrait les fesses parce
he was terrified.
que il avait peur comme c'était pas
Just before leaving, he had seen
possible il avait vu juste avant de
a film about those
partir un film sur ses convoi de
North Atlantic convoys, and one of the captains
l'Atlantique nord et un des capitaines
of those ships was Unfrey Bogard, and
de ces bateaux était unfrey Bogard et un
Unfrey Bogard was commanding in the
frrey Bogard était impérial dans la
storm, obviously, meaning they were firing
tempête évidemment c'està dire ça tirait
from all sides, but he was there, he
de tous les côtés mais il était là il
kept his cool. And Gabin was thinking, "What an idiot
gardait son sang froid ilit et Gabin se
this Bogard is, what an idiot this Bogard is!"
disait mais quel con ce Bogard quel con
And that's what war is like when
ce beogard et c'est ça la guerre quand
you've always known it.  Through
vous l'avez toujours vu à travers le
cinema, you can't have the same
cinéma vous ne pouvez pas avoir le même
relationship to war, that's one thing, yeah,
rapport à la guerre ça c'est une chose
but now we have Jack Bower,
ouais mais maintenant on a jackes Bower
you know Jack Bower, another aspect is that
vous connaissez Jack Bower autre aspect
today
c'est celui-là c'est qu'aujourd'hui
every week you have an
chaque semaine vous avez un super-héros
American superhero saving the planet, so I
américain qui sauve la planète alors moi
proposed, precisely in the
j'ai proposé justement dans la
creation of the enemy, that we have
fabrication de l'enemi que nous on a des
super intellectuals or BHL, but doped
super intellectuel ou la BHL mais dopé
or not doped, oh no, no, no, super
ou pas dopé ah non non non super
intellectual, it's the P concept, it's
intellectuel c'est les P concept c'est
the new concept, it's the new
le nouveau concept c'est le nouveau
means of weaponry. I proposed that we do
moyen d'armement moi j'ai proposé qu'on
a twinning, BHL and Stalin, yes, and
fasse un jumelage BHL stalon oui et
that we send them to Afghanistan, to have a look
qu'on les envoie en Afghanistan à eu
at the term, genetic or not, no, no, no, I don't want to do
jage sur le terme génétique ou non non
genetic manipulation, but BHL wrote
manipulation génétique mais BHL a écrit
two articles that I found in Le
deux articles que j'ai retrouvé dans le
Point explaining how to
point expliquant comment il fallait
resolve the Afghan crisis, and I
résoudre la crise afghane et BHL je me
use this argument for the courses
sers de cet argument pour les cours que
I teach at Sciences Po. I bought Rambo 2,
je fais à Science Po j'ai acheté Rambo 2
Rambo 2, it's the moment when he returns to
Rambo 2 c'est moment où il revient au
Vietnam because he  There are always
Vietnam parce que il y a toujours des
American pilots imprisoned by those
pilotes américains emprisonnés par ces
Vietnamese bastards, and he's going there, we're going to get
salotes vietnami et C il y va on va le
him, obviously, and he says this
chercher lui évidemment et il dit cette
time we're going to win—
fois on y va pour gagner argument
classic far-right argument: if we
classique de l'extrême droite si on a
lost, it's the fault of their bureaucrats
perdu c'est la faute de ses bureaucrates
and politicians. And in the film, he
et de ses politiciens et dans le film il
kills 72 guys, 72! So obviously he kills
tue 72 types 72 alors évidemment il est
himself, right? I mean, with a
tu tout seul hein je veux dire à l' à
bow, a pistol, a machine gun, a
l'arc au pistolet à la mitrailleuse à la
flick of the wrist? No, no, no, no!
doucette du regard c'est non non non non
Because at one point he
parce que quand même à un moment il se
cuts his hand, yeah, really! And so
coupe à la main ouais quand même et donc
the heroine has to treat him, but
il faut que l'héroïne le soigne mais
since the heroine is Asian, she has to die. He can't
comme l'héroïne est une aasienne il faut
come back, he can't bring a woman back
revienne faut pas qu'il ramène une femme
there. Okay, but imagine for a minute that we
là-bas bon mais imaginez une minute
made a film like that about
qu'on fasse un film comme ça sur
Algeria, a guy who says, "We're going
l'Algérie un mec qui dise on va
back to Algeria, this time we're going to
retourner en Algérie cette fois on y va
win," and who kills 72 Algerians. Can you
pour gagner et qui tue 72 algériens vous
imagine the political scandal that would cause
imaginez le scandale politique que ça
in France? And we take it?  Yes,
ferait en France et nous on prend ça oui
but it's not a big deal, it's an
mais c'est pas grave c'est un film
adventure film. Look at the
d'aventure voyez le le décalage
psychological disconnect, the relationship to
psychologique que ça le rapport à la
violence, in particular, the relationship to
violence en particulier le rapport à la
violence. Of course, the
violence bien sûr c'est le héros
American hero is obviously the hero, the good
américain est évidemment le héros le bon
hero, who is more muscular than the bad
héros qui est plus musclé que le mauvais
hero, than the villain. Okay, we'll
héros que le que le méchant allez on va
finish the interview. I'm going to
on va terminer l'interview je vais vous
ask you just two quick questions. The
poser juste deux petites questions la
first one is, I give you a word
première ça consiste je vous cite un mot
and you say "tacotac," what does that make
et vous me dites du tacotac à quoi ça
you think of? The Barin Barag is
vous fait penser le Barine barag c'est
the very example of the black hole of
l'exemple même du trou noir de la
Western strategic thinking, occupied
réflexion stratégique occidentale occupé
by the Saudis who repressed the
par les soouiens qui on réprimé la
majority of the Shiite population to
majorité de la population chiide pour
re-establish a Sunni monarchy. So it's
rétablir une monarchie sunite donc ça
part of those
fait partie de ces interventions
foreign interventions by our allies that we don't
extérieures de nos alliés pour lesqueles
talk about.
on dont on parle pas Saoudite Arabie
Saudi Arabia is pretty much the
Saoudite c'est à peu près la Corée du
intellectual North Korea, meaning it's the
Nord intellectuelle c'est-à-dire que
same mindset: everything is forbidden. You
c'est le même état d'esprit interdiction
have to go to
de tous il faut être aller en Arabie
Saudi Arabia to see what it's like, you know? I mean,
Saoudite pour voir ce que c'est hein je
the only distraction is the
veux dire la seule distraction c'est le
Bachar Mall.  alAssad, uh, I'm
centre commercial Bachar alAssad euh je
just finishing up on Saudi Arabia, and
termine juste sur l'Arabie Saoudite et
so on Saudi Arabia, it's a
donc sur l'Arabie Saoudite c'est un
fantastic, how to say, it's a
fantastique comment dire c'est un
fantastic, how to say, black hole, once again,
fantastique comment dire trou noir
of Western strategic thinking.
encore une fois de la pensé stratégique
Purchase, uh, Bashar al-Assad, no, no, no,
occidentale achat euh Bachar alAssad non
purchase in France by
non non achat en France par les capitaux
Qatari capital, that doesn't bother me as long as it's
Qatar moi ça ne me gêne pas à partir du
managed. For
moment où on les gère c'est-à-dire par
example, when Qatar decided to
exemple quand le Qatar avait décidé de
create an intervention fund for the
faire une fond d'intervention pour les
French suburbs, as long as
banlieux françaises à partir du moment
the government said okay, but it would
où le gouvernement a dit d'accord mais
be 50/50, or even 50 plus one
ce sera du 50 50 et même du 50 plus une
vote on 50%, I have nothing against it. We're
voix sur 50 % j'ai rien contre on est en
short of capital, and so that doesn't bother me,
mal de capital et donc ça ça ne me gêne
provided that, once again, it's
pas à condition que encore une fois ce
monitored, managed, and done in accordance with the
soit surveillé géré et fait dans la
philosophy of the French Republic.
philosophie de la République française
Bashar al-
bacharassad
Assad is interesting
ben Bachar alAssad c'est intéressant
because it shows how
parce que justement ça montre combien
difficult it is today to do things in
aujourd'hui il est difficile de faire du
black and white like we did during
noir et blanc comme on faisait à
the Cold War, because
l'époque de la guerre froide parce que
suddenly we ask ourselves, which of
tout à coup on se dit mais lequel des
the solutions is the...
lequel laquelle des solutions est la
Worse still, when you don't know the worst
pire et quand on ne sait pas quelle est
solution, the best is
la solution la pire le mieieux c'est de
not to intervene. We've never managed to
pas intervenir on a jamais réussi à
stop a civil war through
arrêter une guerre civile par une
external military intervention.
intervention extérieure militaire
Gaddafi, Gaddafi, Gaddafi—I admit that
Kaddafi Kaddafi Kaddafi j'avoue que là
we were in the same situation there too. No
aussi on était dans la même situation
one could truly
personne ne pouvait véritablement
foresee the disintegration of the country once
prévoir la décomposition du pays une
they
disparition une fois qu'ils auraient
disappeared. So, a kind of
disparus donc il y a eu une espèce de
fuse was lit. We didn't know
mèche qui a été allumée on ne savait pas
the intensity of the explosion,
quelle était l'intensité de l'explosion
but we're coming back to something that
mais on revient sur quelque chose qui
should be one of the observations we need to
devrait être un ces constats qu'il faut
make today: we must
faire aujourd'hui c'est que il faut
stop overusing the military
cesser de surutiliser l'outil militaire
when we don't want to bother with
quand on ne veut pas se donner la peine
political analysis. John
d'analyser politiquement John
McCen is the French
mccen c'est le fabricant de
fry maker. Laurent Fabius—well, Laurent Fabius
frites Laurent Fabius ben Laurent Fabius
is interesting because it's the
c'est intéressant parce que c'est une
trajectory of those types who, precisely
trajectoire de ces type qui justement
today, are among the
aujourd'hui font partie des
neoconservatives who came to power,
néoconservateurs arrivés au pouvoir euh
who don't refuse any re-examination of their
qui ne se refuse à tout réexamen de sa
own policies, while the
propre politique euh alors que les
Americans are normalizing
Américains sont en train de normaliser
their relationship with Iran for reasons
leur relation à l'Iran pour des raisons
Besides, we understand, right? Because we
d'ailleurs qu'on comprend hein parce
need the Iranians to
qu'on a besoin des Iraniens pour
resolve the crises in Afghanistan,
résoudre la crise en Afghanistan au
Pakistan, Lebanon, Syria, and Iraq, which
Pakistan en Liban en Syrie en Irak ce
is quite something. We still have
qui est quand même pas mal on a toujours
a president who stands alone at the bow of
un président qui campe seul au à l'avant
the Titanic, saying, "I know how to put the
du Titanic en disant je su le mettre du
world to rights." Well, the problem is,
monde bon le problème c'est que le
you know the rest of the Titanic
Titanic vous connaissez la suite de
story, right? Okay, last question:
l'histoire hein allez dernière question
if you had to leave a message in a
si vous aviez laissé si vous aviez à
bottle on the
laisser une bouteille à la mer sur
internet, we'll make you mortal
Internet on va vous rendre mortel
today. If you had to leave a message in a
aujourd'hui si vous aviez à laisser une
bottle on the internet for
bouteille sur Internet pour les jeunes
the younger generations, do
générations pour les jeunes générations
you have any advice to
est-ce que vous avez un conseil à leur
give them, something to maximize their
donner quelque chose pour maximiser leur
intellectual defense against the
défense intellectuelle contre la
dialectic of
dialectique de la
Newspeak? It's an extremely
novlangue c'est une question extrêmement
difficult question, right? Because there was already
difficile hein parce que il y a déjà eu
a first slogan that had
une première un premier slogan qui a eu
extraordinary popularity: "
une extraordinaire popularité c'était le
Indignez-vous!" (Time for Outrage!) by C. Fanel. I would
indignez-vous de C Fanel moi je leur
tell them: work, study, watch,
diraiis travailler étudier regardez
learn. It's really the only
apprenez c'est vraiment la seule
protection we have today against
protection qu'on est aujourd'hui contre
this kind of flood of
cette espèce de flot d'information
immediate information. Give yourselves time to
immédiate donnez-vous le temps de
think, reflect, plagiarize, yes, and
réfléchir reporterend réfléchir plagir
above all, learn.  Learning, learning, that's what
oui puis surtout apprendre apprendre
this kind
apprendre c'est ça qui est cette espèce
of society is all about, this paradoxical situation
de notre société à ce site paradoxal
where we might say, "But at 20, you
qu'on peut se dire mais à 20 ans vous
can be a billionaire if you become a
pouvez être milliardaire si vous devenez
footballer or a crooner, you suddenly
footballeur ou chanteur de charme vous
become a billionaire." So, if
devenez tout à coup milliardaire donc si
you will, there's a degradation of
vous voulez là il y a une dégradation de
knowledge here. These trajectories are
la connaissance ces trajectoires là sont
incredibly
des trajectoires incroyablement
seductive for young people, but we
séduisantes pour des jeunes or on ne
can never avoid
pourra pas jamais faire l'économie de
knowing, even when faced
savoir quand même le jour où on se
with difficulty, what
trouve face à la difficulté quelle
stance to take. Look at the
posture prendre regardez pendant la
scandal during the
l'occupation un scandale pendant
Occupation. It's easy today to
l'occupation c'est facile aujourd'hui de
say you should have been in the Resistance,
dire il fallait être dans la résistance
but the people who faced this
mais les gens qui étaient face à ce
problem—it was 3 or 9% of the
problème là Ctait 3 ou 9 % de la
population—had to have this
population fallait qu'ils ait cette
kind of critical distance that meant that a guy, who
espèce de distance critique qui faisait
was, nevertheless, a
qu'un degul qui était pourtant un type
right-winger, even an extreme right-winger, a
de droite et voire d'extrême droite ass
monarchist at the beginning, decided that
c'est monarchiste au début décide que la
France was something other than Pétain. And on the
France c'était autre chose que Pétin et
other side, we have a Pétain who had
on a de l'autre côté un Pétin qui avait
basked in his glory, etc., who could
aéolé de sa gloire et cetera qui pouvait
seduce the majority of the population
séduire la majorité de la population
because he was the  Savior of
parce que c'était le sauveur de la
France, this kind of individual examination
France cette espèce d'examen individuel
that makes us position ourselves on
qui fait qu'on se positionne sur des
values ​​after acquiring
valeurs après une
knowledge, that's the real challenge
connaissance c'est ça le véritable défi
for the independent person today.
de l'homme indépendant aujourd'hui
Pierre knows this, thank you, thank you to
Pierre connaiss ça merci merci à
[Music].
[Musique]
From the moment we allow
vous à partir du moment où on autorise
operators to do what they want
les opérateurs à faire ce qu'ils veulent
on the network, in
sur le réseau
fact, we allow them to modify
en fait on les autorise à modifier la
society, we allow them to modify the
société on les autorise à modifier la
way people interact.
façon dont les gens interagissent de
Better and better, there are more and more
mieux en mieux o il y a de plus en plus
opportunities, more and more knowledge
d'opportunités de plus en plus de savoir
and talent, more and more
et de talent et de plus en plus de
solutions, and more and more capital
solutions et de plus en plus de capitaux
for projects. What's currently
pour des projets c'estàdire que ce qui
lacking is that in
manque à l'heure actuelle que dans
many countries, the
beaucoup de pays on fait évoluer le
institutional framework is evolving to include
cadre institutionnel pour inclure la
civil society in the debate, and we are
société civile dans le débat et on est
very far from doing that in France. I think it's even a bit of a
très loin de faire ça en France je pense
terror for
c'est même un peu la terreur des
institutions.
institutions